<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony to an approaching glory being an account of certain discourses lately delivered in Pancras, Soperlane, London / by Joshua Sprigge.</title>
            <author>Sprigg, Joshua, 1618-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 126 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10772222</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10772222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45786</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61193)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45786)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1410:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony to an approaching glory being an account of certain discourses lately delivered in Pancras, Soperlane, London / by Joshua Sprigge.</title>
                  <author>Sprigg, Joshua, 1618-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 197, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Print show-through, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:1"/>
            <p> A TESTIMONY TO An Approaching Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BEING</hi> An account of certain Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes lately delivered In <hi>Pancras,</hi> Soperlane, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOSHUA SPRIGGE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eſay 61. 11.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For as the earth bringeth forth her bud, and as the garden cauſeth the things that are ſown in it to ſpring forth: ſo the Lord God will cauſe righteouſneſſe and praiſe to ſpring forth before all the nations.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1648.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three</hi> Vanities <hi>my ſoule is afflicted to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold under the Sunne:</hi> Men profeſſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring an end, but denying the meanes: Miniſters not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne Doctrines and Principles: And Chriſtians not owning their owne Prayers and Hopes when they are ſhewed them again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> 1. <hi>what have been the Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings and pantings of pretious ſoules alwayes, but after the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God to come with</hi> power <hi>in their hearts, their luſts to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, their mindes renewed, the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:3"/> 
               <hi>new creature to wax ſtrong and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in them, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, <hi>what hath been the glory of our modern Orthodox Divinity, but that</hi> The Father himſelfe loves us, <hi>That the enmity is on the creature's part, not God's, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe Scriptures,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 19.</note> God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf, <hi>not himſelfe to the world: and</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5. 10.</note> if when we were enemies we were reconciled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by the death of his Son, <hi>&amp;c. That Chriſt is the</hi> gift <hi>and</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>not the cauſe of the Fathers love. That the worke of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (or all that fell from or between Gods electing men to their glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, was but the excurſion or</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy <hi>of</hi> Grace, <hi>but the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromus <hi>or</hi> praeludium <hi>to glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And laſtly, what have been the Prayers and Expectations of the Saints, but the coming of Chriſt and his Kingdom, the powring forth of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:3"/> 
               <hi>the</hi> Spirit, <hi>the</hi> times of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>to be</hi> all taught of God, <hi>the Lord</hi> alone <hi>to be exalted, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down of the</hi> New Jeruſalem <hi>from God out of Heaven, &amp;c. But what a vanity is it for men to be</hi> in <hi>with the</hi> end, <hi>and</hi> out <hi>with the</hi> meanes <hi>or way conducing thereto? What an unnaturall thing is it in Miniſters to</hi> eſpouſe <hi>the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Doctrines to themſelves, and to be ſhy of all their</hi> kin, <hi>nay not to know their own eſpouſed, except it be in ſuch a colour'd cloathes? And who hath bewitcht theſe Chriſtians, that they ſhould not know the</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes <hi>of their owne prayers: yet thus ſtands the matter with us, as I have with wonder obſerved, and the evidence of theſe things may appear by the ſequele.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>For firſt, the Lord Jeſus as</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 15 45.</note> a quickening ſpirit <hi>dwelling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, informing, enlivening, acting</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:4"/> 
               <hi>us, is the onely Phyſitian of value both for</hi> Conſcience <hi>and</hi> Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 4. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Meſsiah who when he is come, will</hi> tell us all things, <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 20, 27.</note> Vnction <hi>that will</hi> teach us all things, <hi>and</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>through whom alone we can doe all things,</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Acts 7. 37.</note> 
               <hi>that Prophet raiſed up unto us out of our ſelves, who will be heard, that</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſai. 12. laſt.</note> Holy one of Iſrael in the midſt of us, <hi>that is,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 2. Gal. 3. 1.</note> crucified among us, <hi>and that is</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Col. 1. 27.</note> in us the hope of glory, <note n="l" place="margin">Gen, 3. 15. Gal. 4. 4.</note> the feed of the woman, <hi>that lies hid and buried in the woman (the earth the</hi> naturall principle, <hi>or man) a long time, even till the due times of the Father when he is pleaſed to call him forth, and</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 1. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>to</hi> reveale <hi>him in us, that</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iſai. 9. 6.</note> to us a child is born, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us a ſonne is given.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the Deli<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erer, the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the Word that is</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 10 8,</note> nigh us, <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> engrafted word that is able to ſave our ſoules, <hi>that is</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 1. 2</note> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heire of all things, <hi>whom</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:4"/>
               <hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>when the Lord brings into the heart of man, he ſayes,</hi> Let all the Angels of God <hi>(all Angelicall Legall appearances, Miniſtrations, Operations of man, or in man)</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Iſai. 45. 5.</note> 
               <hi>He that</hi> girds <hi>us even while we doe not know him. He</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Joh. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>is the light that lightens us even while our Religion and knowledge of him is but</hi> worldly <hi>and</hi> legall, <hi>while our language is the language of</hi> Aſhdod, <hi>and not pure. He it is that gaſpes and</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 8 9, 21, 22</note> groanes <hi>in the creature (even while it is in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to corruption) after</hi> libertie. <hi>He</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">vv</hi> ſerves with our iniquities, <hi>and</hi> is preſſed under them as a Cart with ſheaves: <hi>And when he</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Rev. 11. 17.</note> takes to himſelf his great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and reignes, <hi>then is there peace; yea,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſai. 9. 7.</note> of the increaſe of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and of peace there is no end. <hi>When the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſa. 68. 1</note> ariſes <hi>in us,</hi> his enemies are ſcattered, <hi>and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:5"/> 
               <hi>all our luſts flee before him. Though they compaſſe us about like</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Bees, in the name, power and unction of this Ieſus we deſtroy them; and</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 3. 10. Matth. 14. 2.</note> 
               <hi>mighty works ſhew forth themſelves when he is riſen from the dead in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 1.</note> 
               <hi>character of the Father's perſon is that Coin or</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">d</note> Money <hi>of</hi> Solomon <hi>that</hi> anſwers to all things, <hi>and can fill us with the</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Eph. 5. 19.</note> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God. <note n="f" place="margin">Joh. 5. 21, 26.</note> 
               <hi>All life and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doth he carry along with him and in his own perſon: for he is</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> wiſdome of God, and the power of God. <note n="h" place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 12.</note> Whoſoever hath the Sonne, hath life, and whoſoever hath not <hi>(knoweth not, acknewledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not)</hi> the Son <hi>in him,</hi> hath not life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore it is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle comforts beleevers with the</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 1. 6. 10. 2 Tim. 1. 12.</note> day of Chriſt, <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 13.</note> revelation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>and the</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 19.</note> day ſtar to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in their hearts. <hi>And</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 10. 37.</note> he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tary.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>This is that</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Joh. 14. 16.</note> other Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>the ſame that walkt in fleſh among us, but another becauſe he now</hi> dwels <note n="o" place="margin">Joh, 14. 17.</note> in us, <hi>as well as</hi> with us. <hi>And this was the</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Joh. 16. 7.</note> 
               <hi>end both of his coming and going away in the fleſh, that he might come thus in the Spirit. This is that coming to which the Law and the Prophets beare witneſſe, and whereof the whole Scriptures teſtifie;</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 3. 11.</note> I indeed baptize you with water, <hi>(ſayes John the Baptiſt in the name of the whole Law,</hi> but there is one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth after me, who baptizeth with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire. <hi>The Law leads us to Chriſt by the experiment of its</hi> weakneſſe <hi>through the</hi> fleſh, <hi>and the vanitie of all things till we come to him.</hi> What went yee out for to ſee? A reed ſhaken with the winde? <hi>This is all that we ſee in Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and our owne performances, till we ſee Chriſt, and Chriſt in the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:6"/> fleſh <note n="r" place="margin">Joh. 14. 2.</note> 
               <hi>beares witneſſe to himſelfe in the</hi> Spirit. <hi>What goe yee out for to ſee Chriſt crucified at Jeruſalem?</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 68. 12.</note> She that tarried at home divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſpoile.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is</hi> power <hi>over that that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and unto that that is good, that is in the deſires of us all, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which religion is but a</hi> Bawble, <hi>and as the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>ſayes,</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 32.</note> what advantageth it me to have fought with beaſts at Epheſus, if the dead riſe not? <hi>So may I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, If the</hi> principles <hi>of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel are not to</hi> riſe in our hearts, <hi>they are not worth the contending for. Who would goe againſt the</hi> ſtreame, <hi>and expoſe himſelfe to loſe his friends and all to vindicate or to get a</hi> Notion <hi>onely? Men and their</hi> Opinions <hi>ſhall periſh, but</hi> the word of the Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever: <hi>and,</hi> he that doth the will of God abides for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Behold, I ſhew you a myſtery, the death of Chriſt is but</hi> one, <hi>and the reſurrection of Chriſt is but</hi> one: <hi>the death of Chriſt is</hi> in us, <hi>and the reſurrection of Chriſt</hi> is within us. <hi>It is without us, and</hi> Objectively <hi>propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to us, that it may</hi> awaken <hi>and work within us. That blood of Ieſus Chriſt that cleanſeth us from all ſinne, is ſhedding in us day by day: For ſo as that place given in to me,</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Joh. 1.</note> If we walke in the light as he is in the light, we have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip one with another, and the blood of his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin. (i.) <hi>What is not this light? we</hi> die to it, we judge it, <hi>and ſo are clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from it. And who is he that thus dyes to evill and darkneſſe? Surely none but he in whom the</hi> Son of God is come. <hi>And he in whom the Sonne of God is come, his death is the death of the Son, and ſo</hi> pretious, <hi>as it is written,</hi> 
               <note n="vv" place="margin">Pſalm 116. 15.</note> Preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:45786:7"/> in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints. <hi>This is that</hi> Sacrifice <hi>of God, even a</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſa. 51. 17.</note> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart, <hi>which is by no other than the appearance of the ſonne of God in us: For if it be not upon this.</hi> Altar, <hi>and by this</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 9. 14.</note> eternall Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>it is but as the</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 66. 3</note> cutting off a dog's neck.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are ignorant of one of the main points of the Goſpel, while we know not that</hi> Chriſt is in us, <hi>as wel as</hi> we in him. <hi>We were in him in his fleſh upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe; he is in us in the Spirit, and ſo is the Scripture verified,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 15.</note> I am in you, and you in me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This mighty One was ſhut up in us long before we knew him, and</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 3, 23.</note> 
               <hi>we are</hi> ſhut up <hi>in weakneſſe and bondage unto the</hi> revelation <hi>of him: and when we know the</hi> power of his reſurrection, <hi>and the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of his ſufferings, being made comformable to his death, then</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:7"/> 
               <hi>are we</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eph, 1. 13.</note> ſealed by the holy Spirit of promiſe; <hi>then doe we beare in our bodies the</hi> Markes <hi>and the</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>of the Lord Jeſus, and his</hi> life is manifeſt in our mortall fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> ſealing of the Spirit <hi>hath been the longing expectation of Chriſtians of old, though we have had a wrong conception of it, (as the Diſciples had of Chriſt's Kingdom) thinking the ſealing of the Spirit to conſiſt onely in a raviſhment of heart, and</hi> extaſie <hi>of joy, but riſing we know not whence, nor how. When as this joy in the holy Ghoſt full of glory, and this riches of aſſurance, is no other than the</hi> pleaſant <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12. 11.</note> fruits of righteouſneſſe, <hi>ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the death of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the perfect work thereof in us, or from our</hi> ſuffering in the fleſh: <hi>For</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 1.</note> he that hath ſuffered in the fleſh <hi>(a text that I open in this book)</hi> hath ceaſed from ſin,
<pb facs="tcp:45786:8"/> 
               <hi>ſaith the Apoſtle</hi> Peter: <hi>And,</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6. 5.</note> if we hvae been planted in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his death <hi>(ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> Paul <hi>to the Romans)</hi> wee ſhall be in the likeneſſe of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <hi>And,</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 9. 28.</note> Chriſt was once offered to beare the ſins of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>(ſayes the Authour to the</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes) and to them that look for him, ſhall he appear, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſecond time without ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To conclude this poynt, what God hath</hi> joyned, <hi>we have</hi> ſevered, <hi>and pul'd aſunder the</hi> links <hi>of that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> Chain, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. 30. <hi>God multiplies not acts</hi> vainly <hi>and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluouſly. In every act of God,</hi> as it is in him, <hi>is all but not</hi> as it comes forth <hi>from him, and is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by us. All is done in Chriſt</hi> to God, <hi>and it appeares in Chriſt firſt</hi> to faith, <hi>but not fully to</hi> enjoyment <hi>(though in order to it) till Chriſt be</hi> revealed in us. <hi>All</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:8"/> 
               <hi>was done to God from the</hi> founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>of the world: And in all thoſe acts the Scriptures attribute to God the</hi> higher <hi>we goe, into the greater</hi> infiniteneſſe <hi>and comprehenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doe we ravell.</hi> Election <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 2.</note> ſanctification <hi>of the Spirit, &amp; faith in it; but in the</hi> manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>and bringing down of things to us, the</hi> latter act <hi>ſtill gathers up and comprehends the former; yea ſwallowes it up as the</hi> Rationall <hi>life containes the</hi> Senſitive <hi>in it ſelfe eminently; ſo the</hi> Spirit <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the</hi> Letter, <hi>and the</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery <hi>comprehends the</hi> Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe that know Chriſt in them onely</hi> immediatione virtutis, <hi>not</hi> ſuppoſiti, <hi>know not ſo</hi> full <hi>and glorious a proportion in him to their ende. It is and muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that God is, and ſubſiſts other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> in Himſelfe, <hi>or in the bleſſed Trinity, than</hi> in men. <hi>But this hinders not the immediateneſſe of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:9"/> 
               <hi>his preſence and dwelling in men. But this ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken to the firſt point, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vince that</hi> many deſire the end in terms, but in deed deny it, <hi>and to hold forth ſome light that they may doe otherwiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As God hath not left himſelfe without</hi> witneſſe <hi>to his glorious Truths in</hi> all Ages: <hi>ſo neither in the</hi> preſent <hi>Age, as in the aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before inſtanced may appeare, though by quarrelling Truths that ſtand upon the</hi> ſame foundation, <hi>the Aſſertors themſelves make it manifeſt that either they know not what they hold in the premiſes as it may fall out with Diſciples (for Chriſts Diſciples</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">John 14. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>knew</hi> whether he went, and knew the way, <hi>as the Lord himſelfe tells them: though they</hi> knew not that they knew <hi>ſo much,) or elſe they let it</hi> ſlip <hi>again, which is that the Apoſtle warns the</hi> Hebrewes <hi>of, Chap.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>(ſaying,</hi> Therefore we ought to give the
<pb facs="tcp:45786:9"/> more earneſt heed to the things which we have heard, leſt at any time wee ſhould let them ſlip.) <hi>Both which proceed from the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving theſe things by or from the conviction and evidence of</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>or the</hi> letter <hi>onely, (a light far below the ſpirit and experience thereof,) and ſo they know them but</hi> darkly, <hi>and as though they knew them not, &amp; cannot ſee to the</hi> end <hi>of</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>them: whereas did they know them in</hi> Spirit, <hi>they would know them more</hi> certainly, <hi>and their capacity withall would be inabled and inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſtedfaſtly to behold them, and take in more and more of their</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>without being</hi> dazled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For want of which they expoſe themſelves to that exprobration of the Apoſtle,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 5. 7.</note> Ye did run wel, who hath hindered you? <hi>And that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious caution of the Apoſtle belongs to them,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 3 10, 11.</note> No other foundation can any man lay, than that is laid,
<pb facs="tcp:45786:10"/> but let every man take heed how he builds thereon, <hi>viz. with</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable <hi>ſtuff, leſt his work be burnt, or how he pull down that that is</hi> ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <hi>leſt he be found a</hi> fighter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. <hi>For if that old</hi> Simile <hi>of theirs be proper, That even as the Seaman drawes his veſſell to the rock, not the rock to him: ſo we doe not draw God to us by prayer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, but our ſelves are drawn to him. Then what blaſphemy is it to ſay, that</hi> Chriſt came to reveale, to declare the love of God to us not to purchaſe it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, it hath been ſaid by them of old time, that Chriſt is not the cauſe, but the effect of the Fathers love: If this be truth, then the love of the Father, and our peace, was not</hi> purchaſed <hi>but</hi> preached <hi>by Jeſus Chriſt: for the cauſe cannot be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, but is declared by the effect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, if alſo as it hath been ſaid of old time, Our redemption by the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:10"/> 
               <hi>blood of Chriſt, were but the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancy of grace; for my part, I dare not ſay what may be gathered and inferred from thence (and yet both Premiſes and Inference have my heart exceedingly,) but ſure it is much modeſty to containe within this inference, That if we be</hi> begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten again <hi>from the dead, (or recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the horrible pit of ſin) to the</hi> lively hope <hi>and enjoyment of of this glorious</hi> grace <hi>(which was</hi> before <hi>this redemption, and all or any the works or acts of God, and is</hi> through all and in all) <hi>and</hi> live <hi>therein. This is only that that</hi> fully <hi>anſwers the aim and</hi> end <hi>of God: as without this, or on this ſide hereof to</hi> reſt <hi>in the knowledge of any</hi> plot <hi>or myſtery of the</hi> way, <hi>or of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>without reaching together alſo the myſtery of the</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">n</hi> Father, <hi>is no better than</hi> Negromancy, <hi>or the</hi> ſmoak <hi>of the bottomleſſe pit, it is to dwell in the</hi> borders, <hi>and</hi> flouriſh, <hi>and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:11"/> 
               <hi>not in</hi> everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And laſtly, if as hath been ſayd, all the enmity be on our part, and we are to be reconciled to God, not God to us, then all that language of</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onement <hi>and</hi> Purchaſe, &amp;c. <hi>is to us, and for our ſakes (according as it is ſaid,</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 5. 11.</note> We have received the atonement, <hi>not God: and we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and bought</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Rev.</note> to God, <hi>not</hi> of God) <hi>and is ſpoken to man and his</hi> Conſcience, <hi>who was made</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>law; and as we</hi> grow up <hi>in the knowledge of the truth, becomes reſolved into a</hi> myſtery, <hi>namely</hi> of ſuffering in the fleſh, and ſo ceaſing from ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But indeed not onely may ſome</hi> choice <hi>ſentences of ſome</hi> few <hi>bee brought in to witnes to theſe things, there are none that hold the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of religion in ſo great</hi> bondage <hi>and</hi> obſcurity <hi>in the very letter, but a teſtimony may be drawn out of their own mouthes, as the Apoſtle</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:11"/> Paul <hi>doth towards the</hi> Athenians, <hi>out of their own</hi> Poets. <hi>For if the nature of God be</hi> one &amp; unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>(as all men wil confeſſe) if</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>be the</hi> ſame <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 13. 8.</note> yeſterday to day and for ever <hi>(as the letter of the Scriptures affirm,) we need ſeek no further evidence of theſe things. Then</hi> God <hi>is</hi> true, <hi>and every</hi> Man <hi>a lyar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> law of liberty <hi>is in</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Jam. 1. 25.</note> James <hi>reſembled to a glaſſe. This law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty is the</hi> power and Spirit <hi>of the Lord Ieſus in the heart of man, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting the glories of the Lord there, and changing us into the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances, according to that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turtures,</hi> 2 Cor, 3. laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now as in a glaſſe ſuch as the face is that looks therein, ſuch is the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or</hi> ſpecies <hi>that is ſeen there, whether the face be</hi> black, <hi>or whether it be</hi> beautifull, <hi>whether it come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the glaſſe, or goe from it, ſo doth the image in the glaſſe (for the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:12"/> 
               <hi>glaſſe hath no forme, no image, no</hi> ſpecies <hi>of its own, but is wholly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative <hi>of the object that looks therein:) Even ſo is the apearance or</hi> repreſentation <hi>of God in our hearts, according to the</hi> work <hi>of God in our ſpirits: for</hi> if thou doſt well ſhalt thou not be accepted? But if thou doſt evill, ſinne lies at the door. <hi>In the one the ſpirit of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption <hi>ſhews God as a</hi> Father, <hi>in the other the ſpirit of</hi> Bondage <hi>ſhewes him an angry</hi> jealous God, <hi>according as it is written againe,</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſa. 18. 26.</note> With the froward thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf froward, and with the upright man thou wilt ſhew thy ſelf upright. <hi>The witneſſe, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denoe, or repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God in the ſpirit of man, being alwayes accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> truth, <hi>is</hi> various <hi>&amp; change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, according to the changeable ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity and condition of the creature, but God all the while through all theſe changes remains</hi> in himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:45786:12"/> unchangeable, <hi>being cbangeable onely in his</hi> appearances <hi>to us, and</hi> in us. <hi>For hee is not onely the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable glaſſe wherein all chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are truly repreſented, and the unchangeable eye and light wherein &amp; wherby they are according to their true ſtate ſeen &amp; diſcern'd, but is the unchangeable</hi> Father <hi>of theſe differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; changeable</hi> lights <hi>&amp; appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances that are thus ſeen by us, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in us, according to another text in</hi> James, chap. 1. 17. Every good and perfect gift comes down from above from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, with whom is no variableneſſe, nor ſhadow of turning. <hi>Yet what pity is it! not onely the ordinary ſort of Teachers, who take for</hi> Doctrines <hi>the</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions <hi>of men, but even thoſe who have ſeparated themſelves to a more diligent enquiry after truth, &amp; ſeem to be of a choycer taſt, yet are dazled with the light they carry in their</hi> own Lanthorns.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>But were this</hi> infirmity, <hi>ſhall I call it an</hi> iniquity <hi>(ſurely it is both, according to its reſpective ſubjects) found onely in the teachers, it were not ſo great, though a very great miſchief. But where ſhall we find al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Saint that knowes his owne prayers, or is not afraid to meet his own</hi> deare hopes <hi>in the things we are ſpeaking of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It may not bee forgotten what a ſpirit of prayer was powred forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people of God in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſome</hi> 6 <hi>or</hi> 7 <hi>years paſt, how our hearts were drawn forth in requeſts, for the Spirit, for the kingdome of Chriſt, for his coming in the ſpirit, for his</hi> Truths, <hi>to</hi> open <hi>and</hi> empty <hi>themſelves upon us: theſe with that fervency and unceſſantn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſome in ſtead of</hi> propheſies <hi>of theſe things ſhortly to be to their great comfort, and encouragement to expect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And now is all that truth we expected, come to a</hi> new forme <hi>of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:13"/> 
               <hi>government, whether</hi> Presbyteriall <hi>or</hi> Congregational? <hi>Is this all the</hi> new light <hi>we lookt for, to ſee to caſt our cities &amp; counties into</hi> Claſſes, <hi>and</hi> Provinces, <hi>or to put new names of</hi> Paſtor <hi>and</hi> Teacher <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Miniſters, inſtead of the old names of</hi> Prieſts <hi>and</hi> Deacons? <hi>I ſay, is this all that comming of Chriſt in ſpirit we wanted, deſired, expected? Hath this</hi> mortified our luſts, quickned our hearts, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified our ways <hi>that we are at reſt? Are theſe the</hi> changes <hi>that ſpeak the day of Chriſt ſo</hi> notable, <hi>ſo</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, <hi>that it is ſaid,</hi> Who may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the day of his coming? <hi>Shall the Refiners fire, and Fullers ſope find onely a few ſuperſtitious</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies <hi>to purge out of our</hi> Pariſh <hi>Aſſemblies? Is this the</hi> ſhaking of heaven and earth, <hi>to ſhake men out of an Epiſcopal Prelacy into a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall? Or ſay it were out of a Presbyteriall form into a</hi> Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall,
<pb facs="tcp:45786:14"/> 
               <hi>which is but a ſtep fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: may not, have not theſe chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beene made,</hi> ſalvo nomine <hi>with good credit and advantage to the makers? O my brethren, theſe are but the deluſions of your adverſary the Devil, wbo if he cannot content you with his old</hi> traſh, <hi>he will turne merchant of reformation, and cheat you with the</hi> ſuperficies <hi>of it; and he doth it by ſome ſuch ſlights as theſe; either he drawes a veile, and caſts a miſt before our eyes, that we can ſee no further than the</hi> letter, <hi>and ſo think when we have attained</hi> that, <hi>we have the</hi> prize: <hi>or if he can not blindmen ſo farre, but that they ſee a myſtery, and glory in ſpirit under the outward form and letter farre ſurpaſsing it: then he tells them, as once the Iewes, when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Temple was to be built (the type of our Ieſus his ſecond appearance)</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Hag. 1. 2.</note> The time is not yet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But be not deceived, the kingdom</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:14"/> 
               <hi>and government of Jeſus Chriſt is not</hi> outward, formal, &amp; ſhadowy, <hi>but</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Luk. 17. 21.</note> inward, reall, and powerfull. It <hi>is in</hi> Spirit, <hi>and</hi> within you, <hi>not in the</hi> perſons <hi>of</hi> men <hi>or</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>without you: it is that that ſhall</hi> deſtroy <note n="vv" place="margin">Heb. 9. laſt.</note> ſin <hi>out of the world, and all the</hi> fruits <hi>of ſin, and ſhall</hi> repleniſh the ſubjects of it with holineſſe and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this Kingdome comes not with</hi> obſervation, <hi>how elſe ſhould</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 17. 20.</note> 
               <hi>it come as a</hi> ſnare <hi>on all thoſe that dwell upon the</hi> earth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> firſt <hi>and</hi> ſecond <hi>appearance of Chriſt are not ſo much diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in</hi> time, <hi>as in</hi> excellency <hi>and glory. And that of Chriſts ſecond appearance, which is</hi> now <hi>but as a cloud of a</hi> hand-breadth, <hi>ſhall</hi> cover the heavens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All things make for this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Chriſt: the</hi> ſymptomes <hi>of it are upon the world, witneſſe</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Hag. 2. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> ſhaking of heaven and earth, <hi>the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:15"/> 
               <hi>confuſion and unſetledneſſe that dwels on the face of all our affaires, the ſecurity of the world, their</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 3, 4.</note> ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing <hi>and</hi> enmity <hi>againſt the</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>and Chriſts ſecond appearance. But above all, the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 1. 30 2. 6. 3. 1, 5, 7, 12, 14.</note> wants and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments of the children &amp; the bride in the hitherto proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; appearances. <hi>Therefore lift up your heads, O</hi> ye Saints: <hi>for the day of your</hi> redemptio draws nigh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now as concerning my publiſhing theſe diſcourſes, the world hath been witneſſe of many</hi> hard ſpeeches <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: let the world now beare witneſſe of the</hi> Cauſe: <hi>I thank God it is with mee a</hi> light matter <hi>to bee judged at</hi> mans day. <hi>I confeſſe, that</hi> in much infirmity of the fleſh <hi>have I delivered this</hi> Teſtimony, <hi>but I obtained this grace of the Lord to be faithfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And here you have them in no better dreſſe then as they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, weigh not</hi> words <hi>but the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:15"/> thing, <hi>and conſider the</hi> ſcope: <hi>If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> prejudicately <hi>ſtumble at the</hi> truth, <hi>at his own perill be it, I may perhaps be clearer in the expreſsion of ſome things in this</hi> Preface, <hi>than in the</hi> Diſcourſe, <hi>which being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together may bee helpt. One thing I muſt add in this place, That whereas I ſay,</hi> pag. 126. That a man can be under but one admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration at a time, either of fleſh or ſpirit; <hi>my meaning is, That in that degree that a</hi> ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>adminiſtration</hi> takes <hi>place, the</hi> fleſhly <hi>adminiſtration</hi> gives <hi>place. In that meaſure that Chriſts</hi> ſecond <hi>appearance</hi> dawnes <hi>on us, we are</hi> drawing <hi>from under his</hi> firſt <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. Beſides this, I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing liable to any</hi> dangerous <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake with the</hi> unprejudiced.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the time is ſhort, and I have little</hi> ſatisfaction <hi>in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, diſputing, or</hi> wrangling <hi>out theſe things, I deſire to be</hi> enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:45786:16"/> 
               <hi>them; and as I enjoy, to</hi> forget <hi>and preſſe</hi> forwards. <hi>The Lord</hi> Himſelfe <hi>will ſhortly preach</hi> Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>with</hi> clearneſſe <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>and all that cloud of</hi> Envie <hi>that is upon his</hi> appearance, <hi>ſhall not hinder him.</hi> Even ſo come Lord Jeſus. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_sermons">
            <head>The Table of the Sermons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SERM, I. <hi>The foundation of a Chriſtian, all laid in his being nothing in himſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. 6. I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life, no man commeth unto the Father but by me. <hi>pag.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>SERM. II. <hi>Somthing of the myſtery of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ather, and of Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18. 25. Hitherto I have ſpoken to you in
<pb facs="tcp:45786:16"/> parables, the time commeth when I will ſpeak to you no more in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, but I will ſhew you plainly of the Father. <hi>pag.</hi> 33</item>
               <item>SERM. III. <hi>The Truth as it is in Ieſus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 19. And for their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelfe, that they may be ſanctified through the truth. <hi>pag.</hi> 66</item>
               <item>SERM. IV. <hi>On the ſame Text.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SERM. V. <hi>The dying and the living Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 8. For whether we live we live unto the Lord, or whether we die we die unto the Lord.</item>
               <item>SERM. VI. <hi>On the ſame Text.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>SERM. VII. <hi>Solace for Saints in the ſaddeſt times.</hi> On Canticles the firſt.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:17"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 39. line 9. for the [uſe] of a parable, read the [nature] &amp;c. p. 102. l. 1, 2, 3. for ſo] in each line read ſee. p. 114. l. 10. for fulfilled r. ſatisfied. p. 118. l. ult. for eternall title r. externall. p. 119, at Reaſ. for this Reaſon r. the Reaſon. p. 122. l. 19. for enquire r. enquired. p. 126. l. 9. for firſt read next. l. 13. after fleſhly ſupply appearance.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Sermon on <hi>Geneſis</hi> there is bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for betterneſſe; I know not the page.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45786:17"/>
            <div type="sermon">
               <head>THE Foundation of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ALL Laid in his being Nothing In Himſelf.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>GEN. 5. 24.</bibl>
                  <q>And Enoch walked with God, and was not, for God took him.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU have here the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of his days, one that doth make the Holy Ghoſt (as it were) to make a <hi>digreſsion,</hi> (a digreſſion in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:) you have a word here that is like a <hi>Star</hi> in the mids of the <hi>Clouds;</hi> you have a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45786:18"/> before and after this, that you are ready to ſay when you read it, <hi>What profit is it?</hi> nothing but a <hi>Chronologie</hi> and a <hi>Genealogie,</hi> a deſcent of perſons; but here is that which is enough to take up the meditation of a whole Chapter, <hi>Enoch walked with God, &amp;c.</hi> Of all the reſt it is ſaid, that they lived ſo long, and begat ſo many ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but when the Holy Ghoſt comes to <hi>Enoch,</hi> he ſaith firſt, of him in the 22 verſe, <hi>and Enoch walked with God after he begat Methuſelah</hi> &amp;c. and not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to give ſuch a touch, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt records again and moreover, that <hi>he walked with God and was not, for God took him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which I do deſign, and which I hope [if the Spirit of God ſo deſign) may be for good unto your hearts, out of theſe words is this, <hi>viz.</hi> to hold forth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45786:18"/> unto you, a chief <hi>Character</hi> of a Chriſtian; if ſo be that they were <hi>Chriſtians</hi> from the beginning, (as they were, for they <hi>all dyed in the Faith;</hi> as it is ſaid in the 11. <hi>Hebrews,)</hi> and that is this, that <hi>he is one that is not;</hi> it is a ſtrange Character to ſhew you what a man is, by telling you, he <hi>is not.</hi> This is the very main thing of a Chriſtian; the moſt eſſential thing that can be affirmed of him, that he is not, <hi>Enoch walked with God, and was not</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the meaning of the words, there is no great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in them; the Phraſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of <hi>walking</hi> [that <hi>walk</hi> not after the fleſh, but after the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit] but what is the meaning of this, <hi>he was not.</hi> It is one thing in the <hi>Letter,</hi> &amp; another in the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> it hath both a literal and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical meaning; <hi>he was not,</hi> that is, he was <hi>tranſlated;</hi> ſo we find
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45786:19"/> in the 11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. where it is ſaid, <hi>By faith Enoch was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death, and was not found,</hi> and ſo it follows in the Text, <hi>he was nor, for God took him.</hi> But there is alſo a Spirituall meaning of it, and that is this, <hi>Enoch was not,</hi> that is, he <hi>in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> was not; but <hi>his own being,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and glory was <hi>past away,</hi> he was nothing, but <hi>what he was, he was in Christ:</hi> Chriſt was to him his life, his perſon, and his all; in the Original it runs thus, <hi>Enoch walked with God,</hi> and <hi>was not he;</hi> according as the Apoſtle ſaith in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Nevertheleſs I live, yet not I,</hi> &amp;c. So it is ſaid here, <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, <hi>and not he,</hi> for God tranſlated him in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, tranſlated him into Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo a Beleever is one in Jeſus Chriſt, he is nothing in himſelf, his ſelf is paſt away, he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45786:19"/> hath got a <hi>new ſelf.</hi> God is his ſelf, Chriſt is his ſelf, Now that ſame former ſence of God tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating him literally, that was but an outward ſignification to the world (as it were) of that which was <hi>Enochs</hi> real glory, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> was paſt out of the <hi>fleſh</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> out of <hi>himſelf</hi> into <hi>God,</hi> when he was upon earth; and God to <hi>ſignifie</hi> this to the world, takes him from the ſight of men, and tranſlates him <hi>locally;</hi> This was a <hi>Figure</hi> of that which was done in the ſpirit before, and it is far the greateſt to be tranſlated in the <hi>ſpirit:</hi> If a man were carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into heaven, if he were not tranſlated inſpirit, he would have no joy in heaven, for <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God;</hi> and therefore we are ſaid to be <hi>tranſlated out of darkneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to light, and out of the Kingdom of Sathan, into the Kingdome of his</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45786:20"/> 
                  <hi>dear Son.</hi> And thus having made way, I ſhall come to obſerve ſomething out of the words.</p>
               <p>Firſt, here is the <hi>tranſlation</hi> of a Saint, and then here is the Author, and <hi>Principle</hi> of that tranſlation. The tranſlation of a Saint; the point that I would obſerve from thence, is this, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>That every true Christian, he is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of his owne being, into a being in God,</hi> and this is the <hi>death</hi> of a Chriſtian; <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, <hi>and he was not,</hi> he is dead unto the world, and he is dead unto the Law, he is dead un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own righteouſnes, and unto all <hi>created</hi> glory and excellency, but he is alive unto <hi>God:</hi> a true Chriſtian, <hi>he is not,</hi> that is, he is not in himſelf, his ſelf is paſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, he hath got another ſelf, a new ſelf, and that is God, inſtead of his old ſelf, inſtead of his rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſelf; you ſhal ſee this in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45786:20"/> 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> the latter end, <hi>So then with my mind, I my ſelf ſerve the Law of God, but with the fleſh the law of ſin.</hi> Mark you there; The <hi>fleſh,</hi> a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver counts none of himſelf; as it is in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>You are not in the fleſh, but in the ſpirit, if the ſpirit of God dwel in you;</hi> and ſo in the 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> of that Epiſtle, <hi>How can we that are dead to ſin, live any longer therein;</hi> Sin is ſaid to be <hi>condemned in the fleſh,</hi> in the 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3 <hi>v.</hi> That which I deſire chiefly to bind my ſelf unto, is this, to ſhew unto Beleevers, that if ſo be they be true Beleevers, they have a being in God, and in the Spirit, yea, an intire being, &amp; they are to have no being at all in the fleſh, I ſay, if ſo be they are true Beleevers, they have an intire being in God, and the Spirit, and are to account themſelves to have no being, no intereſt at all in the fleſh. There are they that ſpeak
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45786:21"/> of a fleſhly, and a ſpirituall <hi>part</hi> in Beleevers, and this ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>part</hi> they look upon as that which ſhould be encouraged, that to which all the promiſes belong, but many times they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find this ſame ſpiritual part, and ſo can have no comfort, as in time of tentation; (and I beſeech you conſider that, for it will be a ſufficient argument againſt the going on in ſuch a kind of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion as that is, of a ſpirituall part, and a fleſhly, and the like, (taking this ſpirituall part to be grace in the act; for when they finde not grace in the act, they cannot take any comfort at all, then they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake up themſelves in the ſame heap and dunghill with the world,) but if God made out this to you, that you have an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire being</hi> in the ſpirit, and that it is poſſible for a Saint to <hi>retreate</hi> into the ſpirit ſo wholy, as to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45786:21"/> himſelf intirely, and to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up all his intereſt into the ſpirit; this would be much to the relief &amp; comfort of a poor ſoul.</p>
               <p>Now I muſt ſhew you what are the fruits and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of this, and then come to ſhew you the way that God brings his people to this.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I wil ſhew you the benefit of a Chriſtians loſing himſelf in the fleſh; this is the benefit of it, <hi>he loſeth ſin,</hi> by loſing that being in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the fleſh; pray mark it, he doth loſe his ſin, and the reaſon is this, becauſe it is only <hi>fleſh,</hi> that is the <hi>freehold</hi> of ſin: and when a man is once gone out of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> he is gone out of <hi>ſins Territories,</hi> out of ſins Dominions, and he loſeth his ſin by this means, and that in a two-fold ſenſe. Firſt, ſin cannot be <hi>charged</hi> upon him, as you ſhall ſee the Apoſtle for it, in the 7. <hi>Rom. So then it is no more I, but ſin</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45786:22"/> 
                  <hi>that dwelleth in me.</hi> Pray marke it: Why not I? But becauſe I am gone out of the fleſh, I am gone out of the fleſhly principle, I do not own my ſelf; I have a being out of my ſelf; I have a being in the ſpirit, and there can no guilt or ſin follow me; the <hi>avenger of blood</hi> cannot purſue him further then fleſh, for being in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he hath got hold of the <hi>Horns of the Altar.</hi> Wil you condemn the <hi>Son</hi> of God? The heir of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi> Is <hi>Chriſt</hi> a Sinner? Can the Son of God be under the wrath of God? Why, he is ceaſed to be in himſelf, he is in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And then ſecondly, Sin it cannot <hi>rule</hi> over him, he loſeth his ſin that way, <hi>He that is born of God keeps himſelf, that the evil one toucheth him not, he that abideth in him ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not:</hi> and divers ſuch places in the 1. Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> for it is only the fleſh that the Divill
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45786:22"/> hath a title unto, and that ſinne hath a title unto; ſin hath title in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to the <hi>Old Adam,</hi> and to all the Sons of <hi>Old Adam;</hi> as they are natural, and as they are fleſh and blood, they are the ſlaves and vaſſals of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Satan;</hi> but the <hi>new creature,</hi> he hath nothing to do withall: It is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> You may underſtand it this way alſo, when the Devill comes to tempt a Saint that lives in the Spirit, he doth as good as come and bid the <hi>Son of God</hi> to fall down and <hi>Worſhip him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. As he loſeth his ſin by this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> means, ſo <hi>he is ſet free from death</hi> by this means, ſet free from condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the wrath of God cannot ſeize upon him, <hi>This is my well beloved Son in whom I am wel plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> God cannot be diſpleaſed with his wel beloved Son. When a man is once in Chriſt, there is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45786:23"/> nothing iſſues out from God but love, nothing but ſmiles, and good words, and good wiſhes; this is the benefit of a man being in Chriſt, of a man not being in himſelf, of a man ceaſing to be in the fleſh; he loſeth his ſin, and doth eſcape death and judgment. And therefore it is, that this ſame <hi>Enoch</hi> here, (as a pledg to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that walk in his ſteps) he was <hi>tranſlated that he ſhould not ſee death</hi> it ſelf, becauſe death is as it were an Emblem of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin (an Emblem I ſay; for if the damned had no worſe puniſhment then the death of the body, it were no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but death hath a form of puniſhment,) therefore <hi>Enoch</hi> was tranſlated that he ſhould not ſee death, becauſe he was not, that is, he was not himſelf, he was in Chriſt, who is the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45786:23"/>
               <p> Yea a 3. benefit: whatſoever <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a Chriſtian is in, he may <hi>rejoyce in it,</hi> if he be not; &amp; this is indeed the very ſum of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the ſumme of his happineſs, that whatſoever eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he ſeems to be in outwardly, yet he hath a <hi>retreating</hi> place, in which he can look upon all theſe things that befall his fleſh, and can rejoyce in them, and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them; when a man ſhal ſee that theſe afflictions that are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him are for phyſick, not for puniſhment, he can withdraw from them all, and he can be a <hi>Spectator</hi> of them, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at all; he is active in all, he doth withdraw himſelf from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all; it is true, ſaith he, this is upon my fleſh, but yet he doth poſſeſs and enjoy an other ſtate, and another life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and another perſonallity in the Spirit; he is in Chriſt, and as I am in Chriſt,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45786:24"/> 
                  <hi>there is no condemnation</hi> towards me, I am ſure, there is nothing but love towards me, this is the higheſt comfort that can be, for a man to be able to withdraw himſelf from all ſin and miſery, as if he had no part in it, though it be upon him; this is that the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks in the 91. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 1. 2. it is ſpoken expreſly there, <hi>He that dwelleth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place of the moſthigh ſhal abide under the ſhadow of the Almighty;</hi> and that is he that dwells in the ſpirit, this is fulfilled many times in the literall underſtanding of it, that the Saints do eſcape when Common Calamities are in the world, but there is a fulfilling this in the Spirit; when the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> Being of a Beleever can ſtand and look upon his <hi>fleſhly</hi> Being, as if the ſufferings thereof were not upon him, but upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother perſon, and this is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45786:24"/> of the Saints; I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded I ſpeake to the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſome Saints. And thus a Chriſtian evades all, ſhifts all; charge ſin upon him, he ſhakes it off, it doth not belong to him: Lay afflictions upon him, he eſcapes them all, &amp; is indempnified; not that a beleever doth therfore take boldneſs to ſin, becauſe of this; No, there is none doth more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre Sin, then this perſon I now ſpeak of; &amp; the diſcovery that <hi>God</hi> makes to ſuch perſons, is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary &amp; deſtructive to Sin.</p>
               <p>Now the next thing is to ſhew <note place="margin">The Meant</note> you by what means God makes a Chriſtian not to be himſelf, and in himſelf, and that is by <hi>God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing another ſelf within a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</hi> by this doth God put a Chriſtian out of himſelf, by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting and revealing another ſelf in that Chriſtian. What is that? A <hi>Spiritual ſelf,</hi> that is God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45786:25"/> himſelf in Jeſus Chriſt, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a new Principle in that ſame ſoul, a Principle of <hi>life</hi> and of <hi>action;</hi> a Principle of <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> and of <hi>strength.</hi> It may be thought to be done otherwiſe, but we ſhall find, though God carry the worke under another form and appearance, yet this is indeed the vertue and power that doth the deed, &amp; turns a man out of himſelf; it is Gods diſcovery of himſelf to the ſoul; we may think that God doth it by the Terrors of the Law, as there, <hi>when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment came I died, &amp; I through the Law am dead unto the Law</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 9.</note> we may think, God doth it by diſcovering the vanity of our hearts, and the weakneſs of our Principles, for that they cannot make their party good with Sin, but notwithſtanding we are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome: all this is true, but the ſoul is not carryed forth power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45786:25"/> and effectually to part with it owne ſelf, till God doe pawn himſelf to the ſoul, to be inſtead of himſelf, till God ſay to the ſoul, forſake thy ſelf, and I will be unto thee inſtead of thy ſelf; I will be thy Righteouſneſs and thy ſtrength; I will be inſtead of the Law; til then it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the ſoul ſhould part with ſelf, and ſhould not be. So that it is by the glory of God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the ſoul, that the ſoul is crucified and turned out of it ſelf; even as it was with Chriſt; he knew if he dyed, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the fleſh, he ſhould come again in the ſpirit, and that he ſaith himſelf, and diſcourſeth of it in the Goſpel according to St. <hi>John</hi> 12. 24. <hi>If the ſeed fall into the ground</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that loveth this life ſhal loſe it; but he that hateth this life, ſhal have life eternal.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this accompt did Chriſt yield
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45786:26"/> up himſelf cheerfully to death. Therefore it is ſaid, that Jeſus Chriſt by the eternal ſpirit offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up himſelf; it was by the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſpirit, that reveals the glorious deſign of the Father in his death, that Chriſt was brought to yield himſelf unto death. Now the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees by which this death of ſelf is accompliſhed, are theſe three.</p>
               <p>Firſt, God doth make a diſcovery to the ſoul of the rotteneſs of old ſelf, and of the bitterneſs of that ſelf, that is tendered to us of Gods ſelf; this diſcovery is made to us, and God doth together therewith reveal himſelf in us; he reveals himſelf in us; and ſhews himſelf to be our Righteouſneſs and our Strength. The ſoul ſees it ſelf poſſeſſed of God, and ſees God dwelling in him, &amp; now the ſoul knows it cannot be found naked. Now ſaith the ſoul, I may part with my ſelf when I will, for I have a better ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45786:26"/>
               <p> And ſecondly, Hereupon the ſoul hath all its life in God, and his heart is ſet upon God; he ſees God within him, and now his eyes are turned to this <hi>Emanuell,</hi> God dwelling in his fleſh; and now he admires not the things he did before; he did admire other men, and their enlargements and abilities; he admired their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and expreſſions in prayer, he admired ſuch and ſuch acts of piety and charity (which a man may do and ſeek himſelf all this while;) he admired the fleſh, but now he hath no confidence or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the fleſh; he looks whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon God, and admires him, and admires that ever God ſhould dwel with man, that God whom the Heaven of Heavens cannot contain; that he ſhould take up ſuch an heart, that he ſhould become the righteouſneſs of ſuch a creature.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45786:27"/>
               <p> 3. Hereupon follows <hi>paſsion</hi> &amp; <hi>action,</hi> 1. The ſoul hereupon hath all its <hi>comforts</hi> from God, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects all his <hi>courſes</hi> to God; and he ſaith now, <hi>Aſhur ſhal not ſave us, we will not ride upon Horſes;</hi> we have made mention of other names, and other Lords, but now by thee only we will make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy name, even thine: ſo he hath ſweet delight and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcence in God. 2. The ſoul doth all to the glory of God; if a man live in the fleſh, he will be acting in the fleſh; but if a man live in God, and live in the ſpirit, and live in that unſeen righteouſneſs, and upon that inviſible ſtrength, then all his application of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is unto God, and ſo he walks not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, and all his waiting will be for this God; if at any time he is inſenſible of his preſence, he waits upon God, he ſaith not, if it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45786:27"/> werethus withme, I ſhould behap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: as <hi>Martha</hi> ſaid, if thou hadſt <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n here,</hi> my Brother had not dyed; (ſhe conſidered not, that Chriſt in the ſpirit had power now to recover from death, as well as keep from death) but the ſoule ſaith; if God wil ſhine upon me, I ſhal be comforted; if he hide his face I am troubled; it is not I will do this, and I will do that, but God wil do this and that; and it is not, if I had ſuch means, I ſhould have power and get ground over my corruptions, but if God ariſe, his enemies ſhall be ſcattered: And ſuch a ſoul is dead to the Law, and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law, and dead to the workings of it, and ſees that the Law cannot give ſtrength; it is God, that of his grace, is ſtrength to the poor ſoul, and thus the ſoul hath entertained God as his gueſt, and let the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:45786:28"/> come and compaſs about <hi>Lots</hi> Houſe, he minds them not; the ſoul ſees nothing in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but his ſoule pants, as the Hart, after the water brook; and this is the condition of a ſoule that is not.</p>
               <p>Now if you ask me the reaſon of this, why a true Chriſtian is one that is not: I anſwer, this is the reaſon of it, becauſe God is all, and he will be known to be all, he will have his people to know ſo, and will have it held forth that he is all; and therefore there muſt be a dying thus, and a withering, and decaying, and a going out of a mans ſelf. I know no other reaſon but this, why God did ordaine that ſame ſtate of nature, before the ſtate of grace; why he revealed <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but only this, that ſo God might make it knwon to us, that he is all in all. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45786:28"/> God was all in all, and would have been all in all, and could not be otherwiſe; for was there any thing before God, or is there any thing, whereof it may be ſaid, it is beſides God? But yet God had not been manifeſted to be all in all, ſo as he is by cauſing the Creature to dye to its ſelf; as if God had created light, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver created darkneſs, light had been light, but light is known by darkneſs: So God would have been all howſoever, but he is known to be all by this ſame forme of the creature dying in himſelf, dying in thoſe abilities which are Gods; for we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is Gods, and what he gives us, and is to us; but God hereby holds forth himſelf to be all to us, after lower and darker forms; when removed and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, we ſee ſtill another and higher bleſſedneſs in God; and it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45786:29"/> is likewiſe for to give us our taſte; he that hath taſted the ſower, is fit to taſte the ſweet; he that hath ſeen the fading of the flower, is better prepared to ſee a living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivity; ſo we have known God in nature, we are hereby prepared to admire Gods diſcovery in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Now before the Uſe of this point, there is only one thing more I will mention, and that is this, That the death of a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is <hi>into God,</hi> as I may ſo ſay, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the ſeed that dyes as a ſeed, but it dyes into a flower that is better then the ſeed, ſo doth a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever do, that is the tearm of his death: (So now I have explained all that I think of to you;) now the Uſe is this.</p>
               <p>1. It ſerves to diſcover and diſgrace the Religion of moſt men that are not acquainted with this ſame dying to themſelves:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45786:29"/> you have many, eſpecially in theſe times, that do come under this ſearch and tryall, and will be found too light, and there are two ſorts: ſome who have advanced a Reformation from that ſame knowledg which is come abroad in theſe times, they have ſet up a form of Religion in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and it may be they are fallen into a form of Communion with Chriſtians; others are ſuch as are only ſtate Reformers, and the time-Reformers: Now both of them, although there may be graduall difference, yet both of them diſcover themſelves, that they are of the earth by this: they are to be known by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of themſelves, by their mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying their duties, and their forms they are in. As a Chriſtian ceaſeth to be, ſoe doe all things ceaſe to be anything to him, and he doth no more admire an high
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45786:30"/> form in Religion, then he doth admire himſelf; all things are crucified to him, as wel as he is crucified to them. But many are like the multitude that Chriſt ſpake to, in the 5. of <hi>Mat.</hi> They wil be very Zealous &amp; Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, leſt others ſhould deſtroy the Law, who preach the Goſpel purely in the ſpirit; and why are They zealous of the Law, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they think they can keep the Law; they know only ſome lower formes of the Law, (but if they knew the Higheſt formes of the Law it were all one,) for they are cenſorious of others, and wil perſecute others, if they will not come up to their form: whereas you ſhall hear a broken-hearted <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>that Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it nothing &amp;c. Paul</hi> ſaw that a man might be a circumciſed <hi>Jew,</hi> &amp; yet ly down in hel with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed <hi>Gentile:</hi> but others by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45786:30"/> their cenſoriouſnes of others, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that they are not ceaſed to be in the fleſh: the truth is, he that doth know God, and doth worſhip God in ſpirit, hath ſuch low thoughts of all manner of outward forms, that he doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judg himſelf nor others, in the leaſt kind by them, for he ſees that which is ſo much beyond, and he is preſſing towards that ſtil; he takes heed how he riſeth up in the morning and bleſſeth himſelf, or his neighbour, in his form: for he ſees much uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of heart in the beſt form.</p>
               <p>The next is a Uſe of direction to poore creatures that ſee and ſubſcribe to the truth: That true Chriſtianity begins in ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and are ſaying, what may we do, that we may be after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that we may not be in our ſelves: that the next word wil tell
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45786:31"/> you, God took him: <hi>Enoch</hi> had been as other men, but that God took him; he had been in the fleſh, and had confidence in the fleſh, and had been ſome body in his owne eyes, if ſo be God had not tooke him; ſo that this you are to wait for, till God take you up: you cannot bring down the ſpirit, a man cannot make an hair of his head white or black, a man cannot make a thought, a man cannot mould one deſire or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in him, it is beyond his power; this is according to that I ſpake in the opening of the point, ſomewhat toward this, namely, that it is God revealing himſelf and his owne glory to the ſoule, that engageth the ſoule to <hi>forget his owne kindred, and his fathers houſe:</hi> Come faith God, thou ſhalt be marryed honorably; I wil marry thee my ſelf, forget thy ſelf, forget thy ſins, ſo indeed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45786:31"/> the death of a Chriſtian is a <hi>ſweet</hi> death: and as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> God comes and takes that place that before Self had; and therefore you have the death of a Saint expreſſed in this manner, <hi>Into thy hands, O Lord, I commend my ſpirit.</hi> God is there to receive the ſoul, or elſe the ſoul would never be content to go out of the body, and ſo it is here ſpiritually.</p>
               <p>And the 3. and laſt Uſe is this, A Hint or Diſcovery to what end death is ordained, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall death that we looke upon with ſo much fear, and with ſuch a ſad reflection upon our ſelves, when we think of our ſelves. I muſt ere long dye, and be among the dead. This is our Ignorance, what is death? What is it for? It is but an outward forme and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of that work, that God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45786:32"/> in the ſpirit of a Saint doth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day; for what is the life of a Saint, but a continual dying into the hands of God, his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs expires into the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God; God increaſeth in him, and himſelf decreaſeth; he hath leſs thoughts of himſelf, and his own ſtrength, and hath high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thoughts of God; he doth leſs know himſelf after the fleſh, and according to outward appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and he more judgeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as he is in God, and as in Chriſt Jeſus; ſo that a Beleever dyes dayly, and when God hath finiſhed his whole worke upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> then he will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the form of death; when he hath brought his people to dye to themſelves and to the world, as he wil in the latter days, then death ſhal be <hi>ſwallowed up;</hi> for as we ſee how men are when they are dead, they mind no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45786:32"/> a Child no longer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves his Father when he is dead, ceaſeth to act to the relation, and ceaſeth to act to the objects of this world; ſtrew fine ſweet flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers before a dead corps, the corps ſmels them not; and bring good chear before dead corps, the corps taſts it not; ſo ſhal Saints be to ſin and this world: And thus I am perſwaded God would not have continued death in the world, ſince he hath reconciled the world, but to teach the world. And what are all theſe changes when a ſoul is gone to God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is it any terrible thing for ſuch an one to dye? It was the ſpeech of one of precious memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in this City, when he was dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſaith he, <hi>I ſhal but change my place, not my company;</hi> he walked as <hi>Enoch</hi> did: So it is with us in all our changes that befal us, they are but the outward formes and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45786:33"/> ſignifications of that which is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every day, therefore we are not to judge according to the ſight of our eyes, not reckon our ſelves by our duties, and our graces and performances; not reckon by that power we ſee in our ſelves to reſiſt ſin, or act in duties, but look to an inviſible preſence of the ſpirit in ourſouls, that can never be taken from us, which Mothes cannot corrupt, and where Thieves cannot break through and ſteal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:45786:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SOMETHING</hi> OF THE MYSTERY OF THE FATHER AND OF CHRIST.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>JOHN. 16. 25.</bibl>
                  <q>Hitherto have I ſpoken to you in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables; the time cometh when I wil ſpeak to you no more in Parables, but I wil ſhew you plainly of the Father.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the words of our Saviour a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſuffering, when he ſpake not upon his own life, but upon the life and comfort of his Diſciples,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45786:34"/> whoſe hearts were ful of heavineſs: and much ado he had to keep them up from ſinking; therefore no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but Jeſus Chriſt did grone in Spirit, and did go down <hi>deep,</hi> that he might bring up ſomething from the <hi>bottom</hi> to refreſh their hearts; &amp; tobear them up againſt that houre that was coming upon him, their Lord and Maſter, and upon them, in being deprived of him: &amp; therefore we finde him here very <hi>copious,</hi> as well as very <hi>ſweet,</hi> beſtowing the whole 14. 15. &amp; 16. Chapters upon them.</p>
               <p>Among all the comforts Chriſt doth miniſter unto them, this is one, and a chief one, <hi>That they ſhould ſee him again,</hi> and he would hide himſelf from them but <hi>a little while:</hi> Not only his going away was for their <hi>advantage,</hi> but he would <hi>come again</hi> to them. This he tels them often, eſpecially here at the 17. <hi>verſe</hi> of this Chapter. <hi>A</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:45786:34"/> 
                  <hi>little while, and ye ſhall not ſee me; and again, a little while, and ye ſhall ſee me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to let paſs the <hi>rectfying</hi> of their underſtandings concerning theſe promiſes, and theſe underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of his; he tels them what he wil do for them when he ſees them again, and what ſhal be their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that day: At the 22. <hi>verſe,</hi> in general he tels them, <hi>Their hearts ſhould rejoyce, and no man ſhould take their joy from them:</hi> And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly; <hi>verſe,</hi> 23. <hi>In that day you ſhal ask me nothing,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>verily, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I ſay unto you, whatſoever ye ſhal ask the Father in my name, he wil do it.</hi> They ſhall have all their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; It ſhall be a day of grace and favour, ſuch as <hi>Herods</hi> birth-day was, when he promiſed he would give <hi>Herodias</hi> his Daughter <hi>the half of his Kingdom:</hi> but this is not reſtrayned to half of the Kingdom; for we know, the <hi>ſpirit</hi> himſelf is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45786:35"/> promiſed to thoſe that ask him; &amp; the Spirit is the Kingdom of God, it is God, and his Kingdom and all.</p>
               <p>Another benefit, and advantage of that time when he would ſee them again, is this, that I have read to you in the Text; <hi>I wil ſhew you plainly of the Father. Hitherto have I ſpoken to you in Parables, the time cometh that I will ſpeak no more in Parables, but will ſhew you plainly of the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> But it wil be ſaid, Chriſt ſpake in Parables to the <hi>Multitude,</hi> but he ſpake not in Parables to his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples;</hi> or if he did, he opened the Parables to them; as its ſaid, <hi>When be came into the houſe, he opened the Parable of the tares;</hi> and ſo he did other Parables.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solu. </seg>
                  </label> I conceive, this Scripture mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth other kinds of Parables then thoſe: for in ſuch Parables Chriſt ſpake not at that time: but under Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables, here is meant, not only thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45786:35"/> very portions of Scripture, which have the <hi>form</hi> of Parables; but the whole Preaching and Miniſtry of Chriſt, as Man; and not only ſo, but the whole Miniſtration and Appearance of God in the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Chriſt, may be called a Parable; and thus were they Parables that he had ſpoken to them in? <hi>I have ſpoken to you hitherto in Parables; but the time cometh when I wil ſpeak no more to you in Parables, but I wil ſhew you plainly of the Father.</hi> And this <hi>plain ſhewing of the Father,</hi> is when Chriſt comes in the <hi>Spirit.</hi> While a Beleever knows Chriſt only <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> he knows the love of God, and the Covenant of God, and the things that concern his peace, only in a <hi>Parable:</hi> but when God comes to do thoſe things in him, in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which were done to him in Chriſt, in the fleſh; Why then doth God ſhew himſelf unto him plainly. This ſhall ſuffice in brief
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45786:36"/> to have opened the words unto you.</p>
               <p>The parts of the Text are theſe two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here is the <hi>casting up</hi> (as it were) of the Diſpenſation or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Chriſt in the fleſh: It is <hi>caſt up,</hi> what it <hi>amounts</hi> unto; and that is a ſpeaking to the world in Parables.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is the <hi>glory</hi> of Chriſts appearing in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in the heart of a Beleever, and that is a <hi>plain Demonstration,</hi> or ſhewing of the Father.</p>
               <p>In this latter are theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here is the <hi>Object</hi> of Divine Diſcoveries, and that is the <hi>Father;</hi> I will ſhew you plainly of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is the <hi>Quality</hi> of the Spirits Diſcovery: it is a <hi>plain</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovery.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
                  </label> I ſhall ſpeak firſt of the former, &amp; ſhal obſerve unto you this point.</p>
               <p>That the Preaching and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45786:36"/> of Chriſt in the fleſh, was but a ſpeaking to us, as it were, in Parables.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hitherto</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>have I ſpoken to you in Parables: The time cometh when I ſhall no more ſpeak to you in Parables.</hi> If we enquire what a Parable is, we ſhal find that the Uſe of a Parable doth agree with the Nature of this Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or Appearance of God in the Fleſh of Chriſt; for to this ſhall I confine my Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>A Parable is this; when there is a <hi>latent</hi> ſenſe under <hi>patent</hi> words; When there are words outwardly ſounding one thing, and a ſenſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe words, that is not concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Vulgar underſtanding: This is a Parable: It is a Riddle; It is a <hi>dark ſaying.</hi> And certainly the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> in the beginning of his Book of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> or <hi>Parables,</hi> (as he calls them) wherein are the Treaſures of the Goſpell; He calls
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45786:37"/> the Goſpell there, Parables. <hi>Prov.</hi> 9. 6. Now that Chriſt in the fleſh, is ſuch a Parable, may be made good unto you, thus.</p>
               <p>There is one thing doth appear outwardly, and runs into the ſences of men. And there is another thing held forth under that, which few do perceive, but thoſe that are ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly taught of God: That which is viſible and obvious, and runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſences of men, is a <hi>Carnall tranſaction.</hi> A <hi>Bargain</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt:</hi> The doings and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt in the fleſh; and by theſe doings and ſufferings, our Life, our Juſtification and our Peace. This is the outward form, (as it were,) this is the Parable. Now what is that which is held forth under this Parable?</p>
               <p>There are theſe two things that are veyled and hid under this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which moſt men doe not ſet their eyes upon.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:45786:37"/>
               <p> And the firſt is this; The <hi>Love of the Father:</hi> This is ſcarce eyed by moſt men, but they think that the worke of their ſalvation proceeds from the kind heart of Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo they look upon his Humane Heart and Affections, as the Root and Original of their Redemption: Whereas Chriſt tells us in this Chapter; <hi>I ſay not, that I will pray for you, for the Father himſelf loves you;</hi> As who ſhould ſay, though I ſhould hold my peace, the Father himſelf loves you. Now this is that which few men ſee in and under this Parable.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Jeſus in his dying for man, was ſet up by God in the place of God, to ſhew us the great love that God did bear unto man: I ſay, <hi>he was ſet up by God in the place of God,</hi> and that not to ſhew (his own) love only, but to ſhew the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Love; and therefore we find theſe names given unto Chriſt, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45786:38"/> theſe things ſpoken of him; That he is the <hi>brightneſs of the Fathers Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon: And we ſaw his Glory</hi> (ſaith <hi>John) as the Glory of the only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtles and Spiritual men ſaw the Love of God held forth through the doings and ſufferings of Chriſt. And therefore it is ſaid, (I beſeech you mark it) in the 5. of <hi>John; The Father judgeth no man; but hath committed all judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Son, that men might ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the Son, as they honor the Father. He that honoreth not the Son, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the Father that hath ſent him.</hi> God is he that muſt inherit all honor and glory to eternity: but he hath for the preſent ſet up Chriſt Jeſus, to make himſelf known unto the world. It was not, that Chriſt ſhould make himſelf known, or that we ſhould lye down in the Diſcovery of Chriſt, but that by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45786:38"/> Chriſt, the Father might be known, and diſcovered to us, and his love; and therefore, it is ſaid; That <hi>this is life eternal, to know thee to be the only true God, and Jeſus Christ whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> The meaning is not, as if it were not enough to know the Father; but that there is no knowing of the Father but by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent for that end. So that Jeſus Chriſt hath fulfilled his Miniſtration when he hath made known the Father, and then is the <hi>Kingdom delivered up</hi> by the Son, yea, by all the Sons of God: when once they come to know God by Chriſt, they deliver up the Kingdom from Chriſt unto God, even unto the Father. This is the firſt thing that is hid under this ſame Parable. Chriſt bears the name, but God doth the thing; Chriſt ſaith, I <hi>came to do the work of him that ſent me.</hi> God ſaith unto Chriſt; thou ſhalt make me known unto the world.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:45786:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:45786:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:45786:40"/>
               <p> But the ſecond thing that is hid under this Parable, is, <hi>the doing of the like works in the Saints, as were done in Christ Jeſus.</hi> This is that which they onely ſee and receive, that are delivered from the deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Antichriſt. Antichriſt cryes up Chriſt in the fleſh; cries up that ſame man Chriſt Jeſus, that dyed for our ſins and roſe again for our Juſtification; but he knows not Chriſt in the Spirit; he knows not <hi>Chriſt, and him crucified,</hi> in the Saints; He knows not the <hi>power of his Reſurrection</hi> in Beleevers; He knows not <hi>the exceeding greatneſs of that power which wrought in Chriſt,</hi> when he raiſed him from the dead, working in us: in both theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, is Chriſts Miniſtration in the fleſh, a ſpeaking in Parables.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the Goſpell ſeems to run thus, as that Chriſt hath done this and that for us, whereas indeed it was God in Chriſt; <hi>God</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:45786:40"/> 
                  <hi>was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. before end. And whereas the Goſpell ſeems to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to us a <hi>History</hi> only of what Chriſt Jeſus hath done for us in the fleſh; It doth indeed hold forth the <hi>Model</hi> and <hi>Platform</hi> of that ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation that is carryed on in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and is revealed in the breaſts of the Saints; I ſay, that is wrought and revealed there ſutably and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greably to all thoſe ſteps and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to all thoſe points and periods you ſhal find in the Letter. The ſame things are done in the Saints in the Spirit, that were done in, and upon Chriſt in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>And now I have opened this point unto you; if you require any reaſon for it, why God did ſpeak to us in a Parable, and why he ſhews us things as in a glaſſe; why he ſhews us rather the Image of things, then the things themſelves; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> it is becauſe of our weakneſſe; it is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45786:41"/> becauſe of our childiſhneſſe.</p>
               <p>It was the manner of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to put wiſdom into <hi>Parables,</hi> to put their wiſe Obſervations into fables, into <hi>pleaſant tales</hi> and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for theſe two reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that they might <hi>hide</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the <hi>Vulgar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. That they might the better <hi>inſinuate</hi> it into their <hi>Children,</hi> and thoſe that were <hi>ingenuous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe two Reaſons may be given, why God teaches the world by Parables: It is for their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake; It is to take them and lead them by the hand, to ſpeak to them in <hi>childiſh things,</hi> in things within their own <hi>ſphere</hi> and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. So God hath done to us in the fleſh of Chriſt. You will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve a man <hi>loves</hi> you, if he wil <hi>dye</hi> for you; you wil beleeve a Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor wil be <hi>reconciled</hi> to you, if he pay the <hi>debt</hi> himſelf: Why, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thus doth God ſatisfie man.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45786:41"/> 2. <hi>Rea.</hi> God doth this to <hi>hide</hi> theſe things from the <hi>prophane</hi> of the world: <hi>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe, and haſt revealed them unto babes</hi> &amp;c. And therefore if you obſerve it, Chriſt did commonly ſpeak to the Multitude in Parables: they had Parable upon Parable, they had rind upon rind, one ſhel upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they could not eaſily come to the kernell. And the Reaſon is this, that wicked and prophane men may ſcoff and jeer at the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Parable, but God doth keep the truth from that contempt and obloquie. The <hi>outward Court</hi> is given to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to be <hi>trodden</hi> down: God makes it not much matter; men may tread down out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forms, and God may let them prophane them; but there is a place where none come that <hi>defile,</hi> and that is the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>truth, as it is</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:45786:42"/> 
                  <hi>in Jeſus:</hi> Gods Truth is Himſelf. We know that precious things have covering upon covering, they have lappings one upon another<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iewels have Caskets to put them in; though the Casket fall into the dirt, yet the Iewells will be kept clean. So prophane and wicked men may preach and receive the Goſpell in a Parable, in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Letter. <hi>But what hast thou to do to take my word in thy mouth?</hi> the word in the Spirit; for it is that <hi>hidden wiſdome that is prepared for our glory;</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith. 1 Cor. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> Now all the Uſe of this point I ſhal make to you, is this; to deſire you to look into your ſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you know any more then Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables; whether you can doe any more then ſay over Parables.</p>
               <p>Examine your ſelves by thoſe two things ſpoken of before. Do you diſcerne God under the forme
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45786:42"/> of the man Chriſt Jeſus? Do you ſee God coming forth unto you in Chriſt? And then do you find the Goſpel to be realized in your hearts and ſpirits? Do you find theſe tranſactions to be tranſacted over again in you? The death of Chriſt in you? The life of Chriſt in you? The Reſurrection of Chriſt in you?</p>
               <p>Now a further thing I aime at, is this, and this ſpecially; The plain ſhewing of the Father by the Spirit, <hi>Hitherto have I ſpoken to you in Parables; the time cometh when I will ſpeak no m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re to you in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but will ſhew you plainly of the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhal only ſpeak, at this time, of the <hi>Object</hi> of Divine Diſcoveries, and that is the <hi>Father; The time cometh that I will ſhew you plainly of the Father:</hi> So that the point is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
                  </label> That the adequate Object (or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45786:43"/> the whole and intire Object) of the Diſcovery of Chriſt and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, is the Diſcovery of the Father unto us.</p>
               <p>This our Saviour plainly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates here, in ſaying; <hi>The time comes that I wil ſhew you plainly of the Father.</hi> For if there had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe that they had needed to have known, he would have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned that alſo; <hi>This is life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John.</hi> 17. 3.) <hi>to know thee the only true God, and Ieſus Chriſt whom thou hast ſent;</hi> to know thee by Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent; as I told you before, for we cannot know the Father but by Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But more particularly and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 8. ſaith <hi>Phillip</hi> there; <hi>Lordſhew us the Father, and it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth us;</hi> pray mark: As <hi>Pilate,</hi> and other wicked men, (as <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> and the High Prieſt) many times ſpake things, that they knew
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45786:43"/> not all that was in what they ſpake. Sodoth <hi>Phillip</hi> here; he ſpeaks more truth, then he is aware; <hi>Shew us the Father, and it ſufficeth us;</hi> It is moſt true, and Chriſt never contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts him; he never ſays no, it would not ſuffice to know the Father. The Father is the whole object of divine Diſcoveries. The Fathers <hi>Love;</hi> as in the 6. of <hi>Iohn</hi> 29. <hi>This is the wil of him that ſent,</hi> that of all thoſe he hath given me, I ſhould loſe none. The Fathers <hi>Perſon: No man hath ſeen God at any time; the only begotten Son, in the boſom of the Father, he hath declared him.</hi> This then I ſay, that which was the ſcope of Chriſts comming downe from Heaven, muſt needs be the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dequate ſcope of the Goſpell: But to declare the Father, was the ſcope of Chriſts comming downe from Heaven; to declare the Fathers Perſon, as wel as the Fathers Love. Therfore he is called the <hi>expreſs I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:45786:44"/> 
                  <hi>of his Perſon:</hi> God did not ſend the <hi>Image</hi> of his Perſon, but that we ſhould know his <hi>Perſon</hi> by that Image. Many take up the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and the Picture, and they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know the Perſon; as when they take up Chriſt in the fleſh; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Chriſt in the Spirit is one and the fame with the Father; <hi>knowest thou not that I am in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; the Father in me?</hi> as Chriſt diſcourſeth in that 14 of <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9. 10, 11. <hi>Have I been ſo long time with you? And haſt thou not ſeen me Phillip? He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father.</hi> And therefore are theſe expreſſions in Scripture, of <hi>belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in God</hi> by Chriſt, and <hi>coming to God</hi> by Him, and through Him: Jeſus Chriſt Himſelf in the fleſh, is but a forme in which the Father doth preſent himſelf unto the world: But what is the Father, you wilſay? Anſ. The Father here is God in Himſelf, bringing forth all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45786:44"/> things within Himſelf, poſſeſſing all things with in Himſelf. God as he is, this is the Father; you know that is the expectation of the Saints to ſee God as he is; Ieſus Chriſt, and all that God is to man in Ieſus Chriſt, it is in a form deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or in a condeſcending form; Righteouſneſs is ſuch a form, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is ſuch a form, Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſuch a form; All theſe are but formes in which God deſcends unto us; they are not God Himſelf as he is. And there ſhall come a time when theſe forms ſhal vaniſh, when as the Saints ſhall heare no more of Righteouſneſs, or of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; for Righteouſneſs what is it, but a relative word that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to ſin? when ſin ſhall be no more, righteouſneſs ſhall be no more; Sanctification is a relative word, that ſignifies peculiarity and ſeparation. This refers to common things, and unclean things; but
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45786:45"/> when there ſhall be no unclean nor common thing, but God ſhall be all in all, and all things ſhall be in a form or appearance, ſuitable to the form wherein they were in God, then the notion of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall ceaſe; ſo then the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the journies end of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. That which is firſt is laſt, and that which is laſt was firſt: The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is firſt of all. There was a time when God lived only in Himſelf, and poſſeſſed all things in a divine form in Himſelf. His own Diety was his Heaven, and was all unto him. The time cometh, when theſe things that are brought forth in a diſtinction from God in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per beings of their own, ſhal be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and marryed to him, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to that Original whence they ſprang, and live in his life, and ſhine in his glory. And ſo the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is the firſt, ſhall be the laſt alſo. The end muſt find the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45786:45"/> as the year is diſcribed to you, by ſuch an emblem of a Snake, taking his tayl in his mouth, the end running into the beginning; all things came from God, and God by all things ſhews Himſelf. All things are Pictures and Emblems of God, and eſpecially Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; and the Saints they ſhew forth the vertues and the praiſes of God, but all theſe things they muſt, they do wheel about, until the end doth find the beginning, and ſo God ſhal be all in all: When God hath made known himſelf by his Sonne unto the Saints, then ſhal God ceaſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring any longer to the world, as he hath done by our fleſh, and by the man Chriſt Ieſus; but God Himſelf ſhall be all in all. So that by the Father here I mean not a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity, but rather the <hi>whole Trinity</hi> conſidered eſſentially &amp; originally as containing in them that ſtate &amp; appearance of things
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45786:46"/> which was their firſt and Originall glory, which is ſaid in Scripture to be in the form of God, which this preſent ſtate and appearance waits to be cloathed withall, and to be ſwallowed up in, ſo as to ſubſiſt, act and live in that, and not in their own, yet their own not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by this, nor mixed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded by this, but cloathed upon with this; and ſo of Chriſt it is ſaid, that he ſhal come in the glory of the Father: Chriſt is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but is ſtil, and keeps his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct being, but this being lives, acts and appears in the Glory of the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> Now if you ask me the Reaſon of this: why! is it not all the Reaſon in the world, that God ſhould only be, and only appear, and only be glorified? He may lend his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for a time, and may lend his name for a time unto others, that they may make him known unto
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45786:46"/> the world; as a King may lend his Kingly Honor to ſome Leiutenant in another Country (as ſuppoſe in <hi>Ireland)</hi> that ſo that Country may be Conquered for him, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for him; but when it is done, we know all derivative power and authority, and names whatſoever, do yield up to thoſe from whom they receive their Commiſſion, when they have done, that for which they had their Commiſſion; and ſo it is in this caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
                  </label> To apply this ſame truth, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you in the fear of God, not to miſtake me, nor wilfully to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert what I ſay. Let us take heed of Idolizing even the humanity of Ieſus Chriſt Himſelf; of Idolizing his doings or his ſufferings; We ſee God through theſe doings or ſufferings of Ieſus Chriſt for us, as through a Glaſs; but it is no Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to ſay, that a Beleever may come to ſee a Love of God born
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45786:47"/> unto him, above and before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of it in the ſufferings of Ieſus Chriſt. He may ſee it in God Himſelf, though by Chriſt. Do not think you know as much as you need to know, and as much as is the intereſt of your life and happineſs to know, in knowing the fleſh of Chriſt, in knowing the man, Chriſt Ieſus; for unleſs you know God in his appearance under that form; you miſtake Chriſt, and make him an Idol: <hi>I am nothing</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt,) the fleſh profits nothing; He that ſends, is greater then he that is ſent,</hi> Chriſt ſaith ſo himſelf: If God be greater then Chriſt, then Chriſt himſelf is but a Medium, through which you come to be acquainted with God, and in which you muſt not reſt: There is no compariſon between that which is infinite. If ſo be that Chriſt himſelf; if the man Chriſt Ieſus were eternall life, he would not have ſaid; The Father
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45786:47"/> is greater then I. No, know the Father by Chriſt is eternall life. Take heed of being offended, when you ſhal hear ſuch like Doctrine as this; that the ſufferings of Ieſus Chriſt in the fleſh for us, were, as it were, but a Parable in which God ſpake to us; and that Gods Heart was not ſet upon the very having of a little blood for the ſins of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but that herein he premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, if we look upon it in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall contrivance, would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his love to us, and herein if we relate to the lapſed eſtate, he conſiders us poor creatures as we are, and ſpeaks to our childiſhneſs and weakneſſe; who being made under ſuch a Law, and having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred the curſe, could not ſee how there could be reconciliation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blood-ſhedding. Be not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when as you hear that there is a greater work done, in the Spirit, in the Saints, then was the offering
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45786:48"/> up the fleſh of Chriſt: That there is a greater Sacrifice offered up to God, when as the old <hi>Adam;</hi> mans own Righteouſneſs and Strength is crucified, and is offered up unto God; I ſay, a greater Sacrifice, then the very Sacrificing of the fleſh of Chriſt him ſelf; that is, if you take the Sacrifice of Chriſt without the Myſtery; for that Sacrifice was indeed the root, as wel as the figure of this ſame Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>2. And in the ſecond place; If ſo be you need be warned of Idoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the Humanity of Ieſus Chriſt; we had need to warn you of Idoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing other forms.</p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of formes, wherein God appears to the world: There is the Humanity of Chriſt, which is the firſt and the Higheſt, and the moſt immediate Form and Appearance of God; and there are Ordinances in which God appears, as it were at the ſecond hand, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45786:48"/> by reflexion; as when the Sun ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Rain-bow, or when it makes another Sun like it ſelf in a watry cloud, which is, but the Sun by reflexion; ſo Ordinances are but the ſhadow, as it were, of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; Chriſt is the Image of the Fathers Perſon, (he is but the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, neither) but the Ordinances are but ſhadows of the Image, therefore take heed of Idolizing forms; your intereſt lies in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Father, not in knowing any form whatſoever; and take heed of cenſuring and judging ſpirituall diſcoveries. Thoſe that ſhould have told the Diſciples, that there was a better thing then the preſence of Chriſt with them in the fleſh; certainly they would have given much offence to them: Take heed of being offended, if we ſay, there is a higher thing then Ordinances, then faſting, then praying, yea, we may ſay, there is a higher thing then
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45786:49"/> beleeving, and that is ſeeing the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and knowing the Father with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a form, manifeſting and revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelf in his own immediate light. Now this I deſire you to wait for and ſeek for, and to preſs towards this point, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe every form hath <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in it, and therefore you cannot reſt in the knowing God in a form.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Every form hath ſome <hi>unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in it, which comes to paſs through our miſtake: and certainly your great Clarks do ſo <hi>criticize</hi> upon the Letter of the Scripture, that they are by the Letter many times led out of the way, and from the mind of the ſpirit: and thoſe that look upon Chriſt, and calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late all the actions and ſufferings of Chriſt with an eye of Reaſon: What a ſtrange thing do they make of the Goſpel? They make it a notional thing. Every form hath
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45786:49"/> weakneſs, and an unlikeneſs in it; you wil never ſee God <hi>as he is,</hi> till you ſee him without a form, till you ſee him in Himſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I ſhall ſhew you what are ſome of the actings of that ſtate of Beleevers, when they ſhal come to be paſt form: Chriſt tells you ſome of them here, <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>In that day</hi> (ſaith <hi>Christ) you ſhall ask me nothing:</hi> There is one; But what then? <hi>Whatſoever you ſhal ask the Father in my name, he wil give it you;</hi> This is another. This is a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever that is come out of a form, that is gone beyond this form, when he goes to God, not in the name of an outward Mediator only, but he goes to God in the ſame Spirit, in that inward unction that is upon him; for that I conceive Chriſt meaneth here; whatſoever ye ſhal ask the Father in <hi>my name.</hi> Now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Beleever hath the name of Chriſt upon him, and hath the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45786:50"/> 
                  <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>new Ieruſalem</hi> upon him, and hath the <hi>new name</hi> upon him; his name is <hi>the Chriſt of God,</hi> the annoynted of God; the annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that is upon you ſhall teach you all things; now then is that man paſt formes that goes to God, as Chriſt himſelf would go to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if he were in diſtreſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He goes in the ſame unction that was pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered upon Chriſt Jeſus: So he doth not formally make uſe of the name of Chriſt, as a man would uſe the name of ſome great man, and ſay; I beſeech you Sir, that you would do this favour for me, for ſuch a ones ſake, but he goes to God, as a woman comes in her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands name, right or intereſt, to a great King, her husband being a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorite of that King; the woman doth not make uſe of anothers name, but ſhe makes known to the King what ſhe is, and under what relation ſhe ſtands; and ſo doth a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:45786:50"/> Saint come in the ſame anoynting of Jeſus Chriſt to the Father; for God in raiſing up Chriſt, doth ſhew to us that he will raiſe up all that are his, as he raiſed up the man Chriſt Ieſus; not raiſe them out of the grave of earth only, but out of the grave of Self, out of that ſame baſe being they had in Self, and corruption, unto that glorious being in God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And then another thing is this; <hi>At that day you ſhall ask in my name, and I ſay not unto you, that I wil pray the Father for you, for the Father himſelf loves you.</hi> Alas, while we are weak, we know not the Love of the Father to us, but think that Chriſt Jeſus doth procure the Love of the Father, whereas Chriſt doth but manifeſt and declare the Love of the Father; and therefore ſaith Chriſt; <hi>I ſay not, that I wil pray for you, for the Father himſelf loves you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now having exhorted you to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45786:51"/> contend towards the knowing of the Father, and living in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not living in any forme, (for all forms are to ceaſe, forms are not our perfection: The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.) Let me give you this caution. Let no man think, there is no uſe of Chriſt, and no uſe of Preaching, or Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Prayer &amp;c. No, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be inferred from the Doctrine: This only may be inferred, that this is not that glorious reſt where a Chriſtian is to ſit down; formes are but helps, but God doth by forms, bring us to know himſelf without a form; and no man knows the Father, but he that knows him by Chriſt whom he did ſend, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you cannot caſt away thoſe forms: The Scriptures wil laſt ſo long as there is ought of them to be fulfilled. But that which we are contending toward, in all theſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45786:51"/> means, is the knowing of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and then we ſhal ſee that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and unity that is in the truth; then we ſhall ſee all thoſe knots looſed, and dark ways o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; then we ſhall ſee that all thoſe things of Chriſt coming, and dying, and ſuffering for us, were but Parables.</p>
               <p>Now this is the ſum of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that God loves Beleevers, and is their Righteouſneſs and their Strength: and Love, and Faith, and All, not thus <hi>reſolved,</hi> is but a <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> that doth <hi>cloud</hi> the <hi>Father:</hi> They were not ordained to cloud the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but they do through our <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> cloud the Father from us: They were ordained, that they might <hi>infinuate</hi> and convey, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our capacities, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Father into us, but as I ſaid before, in all forms there is weaknes; and forms ſhal be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as <hi>time</hi> haſtens to <hi>be no more,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> be <hi>all in all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:45786:52"/>
               <head>THE TRUTH as it is in JESUS.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>JOHN. 17. 19.</bibl>
                  <q>And for their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf, that they might be ſanctified through the Truth.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement</hi> of that Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Chriſt put up for his Diſciples, and for all Beleevers to the end of the world; that Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you have in the 17. <hi>v. Sanctifie</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45786:52"/> 
                  <hi>them through thy truth, thy word is truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſon by which Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces this Petition, follows imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly. <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the world, ſo have I ſent them into the world.</hi> And therefore Father (ſaith he) <hi>ſanctifie them through thy truth,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay; Behold, they are ſent out into the world, as I was ſent out into the world; they are ſent out into a <hi>ſinfull</hi> world, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lewd world; they are ſent forth upon the <hi>ſame errand</hi> and deſign that I am ſent into the world, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew forth the <hi>vertues and praiſes</hi> of God; and therefore <hi>ſanctifie them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>through thy Truth, thy word is Truth; And for their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here is a further Enforcement of his Requeſt: The meaning of it I ſhall give in a Paraphraſe; It is as much as if Chriſt had ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my Sanctification is <hi>levelled</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:45786:53"/> at their Sanctification; their San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is the <hi>end,</hi> and my San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is but the <hi>means:</hi> It is for their ſakes that I ſanctifie my ſelf, that they may be ſanctified: My own ſanctifying of my ſelf is not for my own ſake, it is for their ſakes; and therefore I loſe my end in all that I do, I loſe my end in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſuffering, if they be not ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified. That's the ſcope of the words in general. Now we come to open them particularly to you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What is meant by this ſame <hi>ſanctifying,</hi> for their ſakes I <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> my ſelf. Was Jeſus Chriſt <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> or unclean, that he ſpeaks here of being ſanctified? Had Jeſus Chriſt any ſin in him that need to be removed, that he ſpeaks here of being ſanctified? No, there was no ſin in him, neither was there any <hi>guil found in his mouth;</hi> and yet Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is ſaid to be ſanctified, not only in this place, but in other
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45786:53"/> places, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>He that ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and they that are ſanctified are all one,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, when he ſpeaks of Chriſt that did ſanctifie himſelf.</p>
               <p>Therefore, it is needfull to ſhew you what is that ſanctifying of Chriſt that he meaneth here; what it was, and by what it was.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it may be taken either <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,</hi> for the ſanctifying of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his <hi>Croſs,</hi> by offering up himſelf: Thereby he did ſanctify himſelf, by offering up himſelf; he was crucifyed in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> that he might live unto God in the <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> Chriſt did lay down the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> in which he did appear abſolute and compleat before his ſufferings, but he layd down that glory and that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, he layd down that ſame body of his, that ſo he might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed again in the <hi>Glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:45786:54"/> 2. Or elſe ſecondly, this ſame Sanctification may be meant of the <hi>whole,</hi> as of the death of Jeſus Chriſt. It may be meant of all that befel him from his <hi>Cradle</hi> to his <hi>Croſs,</hi> of all that was done <hi>in him,</hi> or done <hi>by him,</hi> or done <hi>upon him:</hi> All this was the ſanctifying of Chriſt; And it is called a making of him <hi>perfect. It became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, to make the Captain of our ſalvation perfect through ſufferings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo by <hi>temptation</hi> he was made perfect, as wel as by his <hi>Croſs;</hi> and ſo Sanctification here may be as much as Qualification; this did qualify Chriſt for the end for which he was deſigned and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which end was to reveal the <hi>Grace</hi> of the Father, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, in and by that grace; and all that was done unto Chriſt, it was a <hi>ſanctifying</hi> of him, or a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of him, thus to be the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:45786:54"/> 
                  <hi>and the finiſher of our Faith;</hi> to be a compleat type and pattern, and a compleat <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Witneſs</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. Now having explained thoſe words; <hi>for their ſakes I ſanct<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fie my ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is but one word more that needs to be explained, and that is, <hi>thy Truth; For their ſakes I ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelf, that they might be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied through the Truth.</hi> What is meant by this word, <hi>thy Truth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſame word here thy Truth, is a <hi>relative</hi> word, and I conceive it may relate to this ſame Type, <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,</hi> Image or Repreſentation. Theſe two, you know, are members of a diſtinction, <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> Shadow &amp; Truth. So by the Truth, in this place, you are to underſtand that which anſwers unto the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, Type or, Repreſentation.</p>
               <p>And ſo you have the meaning of theſe words: Thus ſaith Chriſt; Therefore am I come into world,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45786:55"/> and have done and ſuffered theſe things before the eyes of men, to the end, that the like things may be done in the ſpirit, in al my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; whereof I have exhibited to the world, a <hi>map</hi> and deſcription in my own body and perſon: <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf, that they might be ſanctified through the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, you may obſerve theſe things out of the words.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Sanctification is a large notion in Scripture; its a large notion; for the meaning of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, ſpeaking of his ſanctifying himſelf; and of his members being ſanctified, is not to defix the thoughts and apprehenſions of the hearers, unto that ſame grace that we commonly call Sanctification, in diſtinction from Iuſtification; but Sanctification is that, in this place, that comprehends the whole Myſtery of God in a Saint, which is called here by the name of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45786:55"/> even as it is ſaid, <hi>By one offering hath he perfected, for ever, them that are ſanctified.</hi> It were far from pure Divinity, to underſtand them that are ſanctified, there to be meant of inherent Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, only or properly, that is, of the Grace of the Spirit working in us holineſs; but he hath perfected them that are ſanctified, that is, them that are ſeparated by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Love, them that are called in time, them that are led by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſo it may comprehend the whole Election and Vocation, and Iuſtification, and Sanctification, and all; and ſo we are ſaid to be choſen, <hi>through Sanctification of the Spirit.</hi> But I ſhall not open theſe places any further.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Next obſerve, here are two Sanctifications: here is a typicall Sanctification, as I may ſo ſay, and here is a real Sanctification: Here is the Sanctification of Chriſt,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45786:56"/> and here is the Sanctification of his members: <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf, that they might be ſanctified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould be too long if I ſhould obſerve all the particulars that the words wil afford, and inſiſt upon them; therefore I ſhall pick out theſe two things only; and the firſt I ſhal ſpeak of but briefly; and the ſecond is that I do chiefly intend.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is this;</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
                  </label> That Jeſus Chriſt's Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or thoſe Tranſactions of Chriſt in the fleſh, have not their ends in themſelves, but they have their end and fulfilling in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf, that they might be ſanctified through the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which is for anothers ſake, (mark it) or for the ſake of another thing to be don, that is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in it ſelf; but Jeſus Chriſts San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, his dying, and his riſing, it was for another things ſake; and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45786:56"/> therefore it is not to be reſted in, nor to be gloried in, in it ſelf; <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt is unto his ſeed, as the Firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was unto his ſeed. He is a <hi>common Root,</hi> and our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is tranſacted in him, as in a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, As our deſtruction was wrought in <hi>Adam,</hi> as in a Figure. As deſtruction and death did ſeize upon us all, in a Figure, in <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo doth life and ſalvation await us all (all the elect) in Chriſt Jeſus. It doth deſcend upon them all, as in a Figure; for ſo the Apoſtle doth parralell the Firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and the Second <hi>Adam</hi> together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. where you may read it at large.</p>
               <p>Now, that I ſay theſe things were done in a Figure; I wil give you my meaning of it thus, and the proof of it alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> loſt all his by a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and ſo Chriſt reſtores all his by a <hi>Covenant;</hi> but we know that a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:45786:57"/> although it doth give me a <hi>title in Law,</hi> unto ſuch or ſuch an eſtate or commodity; yet this ſame Covenant is not the very poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion it ſelf. So this ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, of which Jeſus Chriſt is the <hi>Coppy,</hi> as it were, and is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon perſon with whom it is made; This Covenant gives our Faith the <hi>First Hold,</hi> and <hi>Firſt Title,</hi> but it is not the very poſſeſſion it ſelf: In poſſeſſion the ſalvation it ſelf is wrought, or rather revealed in us. As we do not inherit ſin and death from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> meerly by Covenant, in which we were invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but we participate of the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> and we ſo come to have an evil conſcience; we have the very ſame Nature that <hi>Adam</hi> had, and the ſame trembling conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that <hi>Adam</hi> had: ſo in this caſe, we have the very Death and Life of the Lord Jeſus working in us.</p>
               <p>So that you ſee the death and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45786:57"/> of Jeſus Chriſt, are not to be gloried in in themſelves, or as they reſt in the man Chriſt Jeſus; but we are to wait for the like things to be tranſlated in us, and upon us; and that is the next thing I come unto: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctify my ſelf, that they might be ſanctifyed through the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 21. <hi>If ſo be that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the Truth is in Jeſus; That ye put off concerning the former converſation, the old man, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the ſpirit of your mind, and that ye put on the new man, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God is created in righteouſnes.</hi> &amp;c Where he ſhews, what the Truth is in Ieſus; even the putting off the old man, and the putting on the new man, which is created &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is the Truth; this is the work in the Spirit, done in every Beleever, conforme to that work
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45786:58"/> wrought in Chriſt in the fleſh. This is our ſanctifying through the Truth; and ſo you have the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle holding forth the Saints ſuffering, from Chriſts example; as the Miniſtration or Token of their ſalvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 21. <hi>Even hereunto were ye called, becauſe Christ ſuffered for us, leaving us an example</hi> &amp;c. Mark ye, Ieſus Chriſt is our example: Chriſt in the fleſh, and what was done in him in a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way in the fleſh, that is wrought in us in an inviſible way in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and tis ſaid. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as Christ hath ſuffered for us in the fleſh, let us arme our ſelves with the ſame mind; for he that hath ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fleſh hath ceaſed from ſin.</hi> Mark it here: The Apoſtle doth not ſay we have ceaſed from ſin, by Chriſts ſuffering in the fleſh for us, but be doth admoniſh us here of a perſonal ſuffering, if we would ceaſe from ſin.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:45786:58"/>
               <p> What this ſame ſuffering in the fleſh is, I ſhall tell you in a few words. It is to have our life in the fleſh extinguiſht; that, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me:</hi> It is to <hi>know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by our ſelves:</hi> This is to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the fleſh; as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>I know nothing by myſelf;</hi> He did not act at all: to be dead unto the <hi>Law,</hi> and to be dead in our <hi>first</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation unto God; this is the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>We are firſt in the relation of <hi>Mercenaries,</hi> by the Covenant of <hi>Works,</hi> and have a kind of ſtock of our own to trade withall. Now to ſuffer in the fleſh, is to caſt awaythi ſame confidence of our own, to to deſpair of our abillities, and to ſee our ſelvs able to do nothing. <hi>For while we are in the fleſh, the motions of ſin which are by the law, do work in our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers to bring forthfruit unto death.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I will give you one more Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45786:59"/> to prove this, and that is, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 17. where the Apoſtle prays thus for the <hi>Epheſians: That the God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Glory, may give unto you the ſpirit of wiſdom and revelation in the knowledg of him; the eyes of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings being inlightened, that ye may ſee what is the hope of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> And at the 19. <hi>verſe. That you may know what is the exceeding greatneſs of his power, which he wrought in Christ Jeſus when he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him from the dead.</hi> Pray mark it; The Apoſtle doth directly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly aſſert, that there is the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame mighty power in Beleevers, that wrought in Chriſt when God raiſed him from the dead. And the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. ſaith in general: <hi>That as many as God did foreknow, he did predeſtinate to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Image of his Son;</hi> That is, God did predeſtinate them to be carryed on the ſame way that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45786:59"/> Chriſt was, and ſo the ſame things to be done in them, that were done in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> There is only one Objection that I ſhal anſwer before I come to the Application of the point; and that is in <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>In whom alſo ye are circumciſed with the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of ſins of the fleſh by the Circumciſion of Chriſt,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here lyes the Objection, if ſo be we are circumciſed <hi>in Chriſt:</hi> If all Beleevers are circumciſed in him at once; as this Scripture ſeems to hold forth, by the putting off of that ſame body of his, by that very circumciſion of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Why then, you will ſay, our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification tarries not for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the like things in us.</p>
               <p>I confeſs this Objection lies plain in appearance againſt what hath been ſpoken.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall anſwer to you thus,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45786:60"/> and ſhew you how we are circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in Chriſt by his circumciſion; and how it is, that notwithſtanding we are actually and perſonally cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed by the circumciſion of the Spirit, and by reall circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>1. Firſt, then we are circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Chriſt <hi>foederally,</hi> as in our <hi>root</hi> and common perſon; we are <hi>unto God</hi> circumciſed in Chriſt, as in a <hi>Figure.</hi> Pray mark it, it is, I ſay, as in a <hi>Figure:</hi> for thus we are to look upon Jeſus Chriſt; not as one that came to <hi>excuſe</hi> the <hi>Old man</hi> from dying, or to ſet us up in a ſtate of ſalvation without working any thing within us. Nay, he came to reveal the Kingdom of God within us, and to ſet it up within us; but he firſt gave us a <hi>pattern</hi> of the Kingdom, and firſt tranſacted all our ſalvation in a Figure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he tranſacted it within us by the Spirit; and this tranſacting our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45786:60"/> ſalvation without us in a Figure. bears its uſe and proportion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the effecting of the work of Sanctification within us by the Spirit. For thus God hath hereby <hi>caught us by guil,</hi> (as I may ſo ſpeak) even as when we ſtood in <hi>Adam, Adam</hi> falling caſt us all down. So now, God he comes and reveals a ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and this ſame ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> God ſets up as our common root, repreſenting us all; and this is that Covenant that God proclaims from heaven. Look what is the <hi>fat<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> that ſhalbe the fate of all the ſeed; if he ſtand, al ſhal ſtand; if he fal, they ſhal al fal. Now Ieſus Chriſt comes &amp; ſtands in our ſtead, and was made under the Law, and he dyes and ſuffers, goes away in the fleſh, ſuffers in the fleſh, and is not overcome of death or Hell, or the pains of death, but riſes again. Here's our ſalvation tranſacted in a Figure, and ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45786:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> us: As it did fare with Chriſt, ſo it ſhall fare with us; we ſhall as certainly come to glory, as he did. Here is the Type, here is the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Pattern, here is the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, here is the draught or copy of the Covenant written in broad <hi>Characters</hi> upon the perſon of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. This is the uſe of Chriſts dying, and ſuffering, and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf; and ſo we are ſaid to be ſanctifyed in him, as our root, repreſenting us. What proportion this bears to the tranſacting of our ſalvation within us, is this. Hereby we are <hi>brought to God;</hi> hereby our <hi>weak hands are lifted up,</hi> and our <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knees are ſtrengthned:</hi> Hereby we are caught (as it were) with guil, and God doth hold forth our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in a Parable, to us: But if ſo be the work reſt here (let us ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an impoſſibility,) we are but in an ill condition, if we be not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed alſo <hi>together with Christ,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:45786:61"/> really by the ſpirit, as well as cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in Chriſt foederally and typically, and repreſentatively; it wil go but ill with us.</p>
               <p>We may <hi>ſee</hi> what is to be done by looking upon the Hiſtory of Chriſt; but til we <hi>find</hi> the ſame things done in us in the myſtery, in ſome meaſure, we can have little comfort: We may ſee the end of the Lord with us, even the ſame end he made with Chriſt Jeſus; but we muſt follow his ſteps alſo, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith; <hi>He hath left us an example, that we ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his steps.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Now the uſe I ſhall make of this, is to confirm that Doctrine I have formerly delivered to you; that Doctrine that needs confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, and that need be whetted upon us, becauſe we are exceeeding dull of hearing ſpirituall truths; the Doctrine is this, namely:</p>
               <p>That the whole Hiſtory of Chriſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45786:62"/> wil profit you nothing, nor all that you know, except you find experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally the ſame things done in you by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>I deſire to commend this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to you again and again; That the Hiſtory of the Goſpell is but a Parable (as it were,) that holds forth to us the ſtory of things done, and not only ſo, but holds forth a glaſs of things <hi>to be done</hi> by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within us.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you therefore be not offended, when as we ſay, that Chriſt according to the Hiſtory of him only, and according to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration in the fleſh, is but a form in which God doth appear to us, and in which God doth give us a Map of our ſalvation. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it not to be thy reall ſalvation, except it be revealed within thee in the Spirit. Jeſus Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Image of the Inviſible God: God comes forth to be ſeen in the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45786:62"/> fleſh of Chriſt, as in an Image, as in a Repreſentation; it is not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked appearance of God, but it is an Image of God. Now we know the Image ſerves in the abſence of the lively face of the living Perſon; and ſo do all theſe ſame tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Jeſus Chriſt; they ſerve un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Kingdome of God be come to us in the Spirit. A Map ſerves untill a man knows the Country, and ſo do theſe ſame Tranſactions of Ieſus Chriſt, they ſerve as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Monuments unto us; Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I ſay, and Pillars, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials, and Types, of that ſame ſalvation that is to be wrought and revealed within us by the Spirit; and therefore as Chriſt ſaith, we may be bold to ſay after him; <hi>The fleſh profits nothing:</hi> if you only know Chriſt, as dying and riſing <hi>without</hi> you, it wil profit you nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les you know him as dying &amp; riſing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45786:63"/> 
                  <hi>within</hi> you. Error in this is the root of the <hi>dead faith,</hi> wherof the world is full.</p>
               <p>This is the root of that formall profeſſion, of that form of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which men doe advance ſoe far in, and glory ſo much of, and ſhroud themſelves under, unto the perſecuting of the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to the perſecuting of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. This ſetting up of the Hiſtory of Chriſt, being ignorant of the Myſtery; Any man is capable of remembring the ſtory of Chriſt, and telling and rehearſing it, if he hath but common reaſon, and can ſay, as wel as another, that Chriſt dyed for him, and can throw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon Chriſt, and hang upon Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This is not Faith; this is not Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: We have not known how to put a difference between the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and the vile; We know not how to ſhake off the pretenders,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45786:63"/> and knock off their fingers that would pretend to eternall life: Through the ignorance of this truth; we have counted it enough, if a man hath had the knowledg of the Story of Chriſt, and hath ſaid, he caſts himſelfe upon Chriſt for ſalvation. But harken what <hi>James</hi> ſaith; <hi>Faith without works is dead;</hi> Harken what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3. <hi>The Law of the Spirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſin and death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He doth not ſay, that ſuch a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of the Goſpell did ſet him free: He doth not ſay, that the hearing, that Chriſt dyed for the ſins of men, doth ſet him free. No, there was the <hi>Spirit of life</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus, as well as there was <hi>the Law</hi> or Letter, the outward Covenant; is it that entailes life upon Jeſus Chriſtand his ſeed? There is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Covenant, and there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Spirit. The outward Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45786:64"/> is this; I wil be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed: This is the Covenant that God made with Chriſt, that he made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> of old; I wil be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed. Now then they that are of the ſeed of Chriſt, are in this Covenant, as al that were <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> ſeed, were in that outward Covenant; but may not any man pretend to be of the ſeed of Chriſt, and to be of the generation of Chriſt? And do not thouſands pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves ſo to be? Do not thouſands in the world ſay, Lord, Lord, and preſs to enter into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? We cannot put a difference between one or other, except we know this truth; for they ſay they are in the Covenant, &amp; they ſay they are of Chriſts ſeed; and what hold they forth for this? They hold forth the confeſſion of Chriſt, and ſay, that he dyed for their ſins, and roſe for their Juſtification, and this they
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45786:64"/> beleeve, and upon this they lay their ſouls for ſalvation. May not the veryeſt Hypocrite do ſo, as wel as the trueſt Saint. But here is that which puts a difference, when the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt brings this Covenant to the heart of a poore creature, when the Spirit of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, the Spirit of Son-ſhip, revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God as our Father, revealing God in Union with us, our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and our Strength, he doth indeed ſeal us to the day of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption; he ſets apart Chriſts ſheep. This diſtinguiſhes them from the other: So that if you lay your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation upon an hiſtoricall Chriſt, you wil be deceived. If you would have that in which you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide, you muſt have Chriſt revealed in you in the Spirit; you muſt have the ſame ſpirit of Faith that was in Chriſt, and the ſame Spirit of Power that wrought in him; you muſt have the ſame eternall
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45786:65"/> Spirit, by which you muſt offer up your bodies, offer up your fleſh to God as a Sacrifice, yea, your ſelves, and your own Righteouſneſs: This is true ſalvation; Here is ſalvation manifeſted unto life. But you wil ſay to me; Is not this a wronging of Jeſus Chriſt? Is it not a giving away from Chriſt? And a giving it to grace and Sanctification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solu. </seg>
                  </label> To this I anſwer, that it is no gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving away from Chriſt, at all; for we make Chriſt to be all in all in this; only we diſtinguiſh of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There is Chriſt in the Fleſh; and Chriſt in the Spirit; Chriſt in the Fleſh is the <hi>witneſs,</hi> the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>common Perſon,</hi> in whom our ſalvation is tranſacted, as in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure: Chriſt in the Spirit, is the <hi>real Truth</hi> and <hi>Principle</hi> of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and of Life; he is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſalvation within us: For what is Chriſt Jeſus in the Spirit, but
<pb n="97 [i.e. 95]" facs="tcp:45786:65"/> the Manifeſtation of God, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth of God; and unto this muſt we attribute, and in this we muſt fix and pitch our ſalvation; this is the Savour of life unto life, <hi>Of his own wil begat he us.</hi> Doth not the Apoſtle there take away from Chriſt? And yet elſewhere Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>the everlasting Father.</hi> This ſame Will of God brought forth, is nothing elſe but Chriſt Jeſus in Spirit; Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is the outgoing of the Fathers Wil, the Manifeſtation of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good Pleaſure. Therefore he is ſaid to <hi>dwell in the heart</hi> of every Beleever. If you confine Chriſts dwelling to a locall Heaven, you are ignorant of that which is the greateſt joy that can be; Chriſt dwels in thy heart; if the Will of God be revealed in thee by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Chriſt is in thee, for he is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the outgoing of the Fathers Will, and the Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45786:66"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:45786:66"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:45786:67"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:45786:67"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:45786:68"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:45786:68"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:45786:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:45786:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:45786:70"/> tion of the Fathers good pleaſure; this is Chriſt. So that if we give to Sanctification, we give to Chriſt; <hi>For this is the Will of God, even our Sanctification;</hi> Chriſt is made unto us Righteouſneſs and Sanctification.</p>
               <p>But I deſire a little further to examine that ſame, before I let it paſs; it is ſaid, it is a giving to San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and not to the blood of Chriſt; I ſay no.</p>
               <p>For 1. I do not here take San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, as it is commonly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as to be ſuch and ſuch particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar acts of the Spirit: I know that our life lyes not in this or the other act, or in any particular act. Our life lies in union with God through the Spirit.</p>
               <p>2. I give it not only to the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the Spirit, but to the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the Spirit. There is the Revelation of the Spirit, as wel as the Sanctification of the Spirit,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:45786:70"/> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 17. <hi>That God would give unto you the Spirit of wiſdom and Revelation</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>3. There is the Spirit of grace, as well as the grace of the Spirit, and to this I give all, and the Spirit of grace is Chriſt Jeſus; and ſo to him I give al: and what do I give to the Spirit? I give the Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſalvation to life, and that's all.</p>
               <p>4. This is the ſum of all I deſire to commend unto you: That we are not juſtified, we are not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, by Chriſts dving, by Chriſts ſuffering in the fleſh only; that is not the compleat Miniſtration of our ſalvation: (There indeed we ſee our ſalvation as in a glaſs, and it is tranſacted as in a figure, as in the hiſtory,) but then are we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſanctified; when as God doth ſend that ſame Spirit of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption into our hearts, revealing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us the Love of the Father, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45786:71"/> revealing unto us our Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that Reconciliation that was held forth to us on the <hi>Croſs,</hi> but which is diſpenſed unto us, by our being offered up upon the <hi>Croſs</hi> as Chriſt was. For the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. doth in two places ſpeak ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly to this purpoſe, that no man can wave it, or put it by. <hi>verſe</hi> 10. <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin, and the ſpirit is life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of righteouſneſs.</hi> Here is the Death and Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt: If Chriſt be in you, (and there is no ſalvation without it,) then the body is dead; the body of your own Righteouſneſs, and your own Strength, and wiſdom is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in conformity to the death of Chriſt; Chriſts death was but the figure of the death that muſt paſs upon the fleſh of every Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; and therefore though we may ſay, I am crucified with Chriſt &amp;c. We cannot take any comfort till
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45786:71"/> the body be dead in us. And the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place is the 4. <hi>verſe</hi> of <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>That the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us,</hi> &amp;c. Pray mark it: You dream of a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law fulfilled for you: that is true too; Chriſt fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it for you perfectly; but there is a fulfilling of the Righteouſneſs of the Law in you. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſhews what that is, when you are crucified to the fleſhly princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and walk in the ſpiritual prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; though you walk not in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obedience, yet ſpiritually it is done in you: <hi>The Righteouſneſs of the Law is fulfilled in us, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then look after this, that you be ſanctified through the Truth, that is, that you, <hi>in very deed,</hi> be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified according to the pattern of Sanctification in Chriſt Jeſus. Let me minde you again of that Scripture, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 21. <hi>If ſo be</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:45786:72"/> 
                  <hi>that ye have heard him, and have been taught by him, as the Truth is in Jeſus, that ye put off the old man, and be renewed in the ſpirit of your mind; and that ye put on the new man,</hi> &amp;c. Look that this be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But you will ſay unto me; is not this to bring us again into <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage?</hi> To charge this upon us, when as we are bid look, that it ſhould be ſo and ſo with us.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution </seg>
                  </label> I anſwer, it is your <hi>great intereſt</hi> that theſe things ſhould be done <hi>in you,</hi> but it is not expected that they ſhould be done <hi>by you:</hi> Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the working (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) of <hi>his mighty power, which he wrought in Chriſt Jeſus when he rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him from the dead, and ſet him</hi> &amp;c. It is Gods mighty power that works in you; it is God that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies you; it is God that quickens you. Chriſt offered up himſelf <hi>by the eternall Spirit;</hi> it was not by the <hi>reſolution</hi> of his <hi>fleſh,</hi> that he
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45786:72"/> gave himſelf to dye, as many a <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Roman</hi> hath done for his Country; but it was through the eternal Spirit; and therefore, that which you are to do, is to wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God.</p>
               <p>And herein comes the uſe of the doing of theſe things in the man Chriſt Jeſus before your eyes: It is to ſtrengthen your faith and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of having theſe things done in you, by the ſame power and ſpirit. And therefore if you ask me what uſe you ſhould make of Chriſts Death and Reſurrection, and theſe things: I ſay, look upon them as the <hi>earneſt</hi> of your ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; look upon them as the very <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of the Covenant between God and you. God reads over (as it were) all the Covenant before us, and ſeals it in our preſence; and this is the ſcope of the Manifeſtation of Jeſus Chriſt: It is but to <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the life</hi> to us, to ſhew what God
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:45786:73"/> will do upon your fleſh: So what God did to Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo how he carryed him to glory, ſo how he was tempted, and be not you diſcouraged, though it be ſo with you. See how the Diſciples were diſmayed, when Chriſt wrapt up himſelf, for a Moment, in the grave, as in a cloud of darkneſs; They ſaid, <hi>we thought this bad bin he that ſhould have redeemed</hi> Iſrael.</p>
               <p>See what an end the Lord made with him, the ſame end will the Lord make with you alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:45786:73"/>
               <head>THE TRUTH as it is in JESUS.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>JOHN. 17.</bibl>
                  <q>Sanctifie them through thy Truth, thy word is Truth.</q>
                  <bibl>Verſe, 19.</bibl>
                  <q>And for their ſakes I ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie my ſelf, that they might be ſanctified through the Truth.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſame Portion of Scripture that is read to you, is an Enforcement, or part of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of one of thoſe ſavory Petitions, which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45786:74"/> Jeſus Chriſt put up at his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of this world for his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, and in them, for all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: The Petition is this; <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them through thy Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Petition he doth in part ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and he doth enforce and urge it with Arguments.</p>
               <p>1. He explains it in part, that part, <hi>thy Truth,</hi> he explains it thus, <hi>thy word is Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now before I go any further: By the <hi>word</hi> here we are not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this ſame Letter, (for we know this ſame Letter of the <hi>word,</hi> is taken up by every one to defend his opinion, and therefore this is not the meaning of <hi>thy word is Truth:)</hi> But the meaning is this; That that <hi>word</hi> that <hi>was with God,</hi> and <hi>that was God;</hi> that <hi>word</hi> is Truth.</p>
               <p>I conceive this ſame truth being a <hi>relative</hi> notion, is here to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in oppoſition to <hi>form<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thy</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:45786:74"/> 
                  <hi>word is Truth:</hi> The meaning is this; That thy <hi>word,</hi> it is not only a form and an appearance in which thou doſt make out thy ſelf unto the world, but thy <hi>word</hi> indeed is the <hi>very Truth,</hi> (that is) it is thy ſelf, and ſo Chriſt deſires that his Diſciples may be ſanctified, not by planting the knowledg of the <hi>lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> word in their minds; but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffing the nature of the <hi>Divine</hi> word in their hearts, that is, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffing God himſelf, by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf becoming one with them. This is the only means of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; This is the <hi>true</hi> Sanctification by the <hi>word; The ingraffed word which is able to ſave our ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now having explained his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, he <hi>enforces</hi> it, and the firſt Enforcement of it is this, from the <hi>title,</hi> and the reaſon that may be pleaded, why they ſhould be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, why the Members of Chriſt ſhould be ſanctified: Why
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:45786:75"/> ſaith he: There is as much reaſon why they ſhould be ſanctified, as there is why I ſhould be ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: <hi>For as thou-haſt ſent me into the world, ſo have I ſent them into the world.</hi> Mark it I pray, and you will ſee that it is not ſuch a wringing of the noſe that will cauſe blood; when we make a neceſſity of the ſame things to be wrought in us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as were wrought in Chriſt Ieſus. For as God hath ſent Chriſt into the world, ſo did Chriſt ſend theſe his Diſciples into the world, that is, as God did ſend Chriſt into the world <hi>to make known himſelf,</hi> ſo Chriſt Ieſus, when he hath fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Miniſtration in the fleſh, he ſends out Beleevers; I ſay, he ſends out Beleevers upon the ſame deſign to make out God and his glory to the world. So that then this is a ſure and ſatisfying ground, why the ſame glory of the Father muſt work in Beleevers, that wrought
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:45786:75"/> in Chriſt, becauſe that Beleevers are ſent out upon the ſame errand and deſign that Chriſt was ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the world, ſo have I ſent theſe into</hi> &amp;c. Beleevers hold forth God in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual diſcovery to the world, that is, they hold forth that glory of the Fathers working, and diſcovering it ſelf in them in a ſpirituall way, which Chriſt held forth in a fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way: My meaning is; Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are not lift up upon a material Croſs, as Chriſt was, and do not ſuffer without the gate, as Chriſt did; but their <hi>Old man</hi> is crucified ſpiritually, and they are raiſed and quickond by a lively hope ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually.</p>
               <p>This is the Reaſon that Chriſt ſaith; <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the world, ſo have I ſent them into the world;</hi> Therefore, <hi>ſanctifie them with thy Truth, thy word is Truth: And for their ſakes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſanctifie</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:45786:76"/> 
                  <hi>my ſelf.</hi> This is (as it were) the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up of the Reaſon, and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it is this; ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Herein doth thy deſign come to its pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod and perfection, even in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of my Members. Herein thy deſign (Oh Father) is come to the birth, and is brought forth;</hi> for while this deſign works only in my perſon, it is not at its term and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, till it come to work in their perſons; for I am but (as it were) an <hi>intermediate</hi> forme and perſon, in whom thou doſt diſcover thy ſelf for the preſent, with relation to the like diſcovery in them, through the ſpirit, afterwards; And therefore (ſaith he) <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf, that &amp;c.</hi> As who ſhould ſay; If it were not in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, there ſhould be no ſuch thing as my dying, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and riſing again; It is but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to their Sanctification, that the ſame glory may work in them
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:45786:76"/> in the Spirit, conformable to this pattern of mine in the fleſh. And thus you have the meaning of the words; <hi>For their ſakes I ſanctifie my ſelf, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which I ſhal inſiſt upon at this time, is the laſt word of the Text, <hi>Through thy Truth:</hi> So that the Obſervation that I would ground thereupon, is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
                  </label> That that Glory of the Father, which works in the body of Chriſt, the Saints, is the Truth of that ſame Image that did appear in the head of that body, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>It is called an Image, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> we all, as in a glaſs, behold the Glory of the Lord; (there it is equivalently called an Image; for your face in a glaſs, is but an Image of your face;) but it follows more expreſly: <hi>And are changed into the ſame Image from glory to glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtil I deſire you to carry that along, that a Beleevers crucifying
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:45786:77"/> is not a <hi>fleſhly</hi> crucifying, as Chriſts was, but his <hi>Old man</hi> is crucified by ſpiritually diſcoveries. This is the Truth, and the other is but the form.</p>
               <p>Now I muſt explain my ſelf here: You wil ask me, whether that ſame work of God, that is wrought in the hearts of Beleevers, be their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life, their happineſs and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? Whether that be their Righteouſneſs; for there is a great prejudice againſt Doctrines of this kind; as if we did take away from Chriſt, and give to that work of God within us, that honour that is due to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Now I conceive that neither the Actions of God in Chriſt, (I mean of Chriſt dying and riſing) nor the like Actions of the Spirit in us, conforming us unto Chriſt, are our ſalvation, or eternall life, but the making out of eternal life; they are only the <hi>Manifestation</hi> of that
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:45786:77"/> grace that was given us before the world began. If you ask me then what is our happineſs and our life; I conceive that God alone is our happineſs, God in union with us. Mark it; not only God loving us, for love is but an expreſſion to us. Love is a ſweet thing among the creatures, and we know what love is from one to another; but the Love of God to us, is but the making out of a kind of ſpiritual Union that is between God and a Beleever; So that to ſay, that the Love of God placed upon us is our happineſs, is too weak, and too low an expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but this is our happineſs that we are in God, and in Jeſus Chriſt; and that the Father and the Son is in us, and is our Righteouſneſs and our Strength in Union with us; This is our happineſs and eternall Life.</p>
               <p>Now I ſay, all the Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God are but to make out
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:45786:78"/> theſe things unto us.</p>
               <p>Give me leave to illuſtrate it to you, by going a little about. This was our Lot and Portion, from the beginning; God was our Portion, and God did maintain our Lot, as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 16. And God was become in Union with the creature: This was in the beginning of the Creation, and this was in the Perſon of Chriſt Ieſus, as an Earneſt of the whole; but this ſame Union, and this great happineſs, that the creature might be ſenſible of it, and that it might come home with the greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, (as it were) and we might have the more lively taſte of it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did God ordain all thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening adminiſtrations: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he makes the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> as a figure of Chriſt, and therefore he beſtows but a little grace on <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> or makes him mutable that he might fall, that the Love of the Father might be the more manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:45786:78"/> to us, which we could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have ſeen, nor admired ſo much, if we had not been thus led about unto it. And this is the end of Chriſt in the Fleſh, and Chriſt in the Spirit; and ſo I ſhal come to ſhew you the difference betweene Chriſt in the Fleſh, and Chriſt in the Saints; for if we give glory to any other then unto Chriſt, we ſhoot beſide the mark; we give it to Chriſt ſtil; but there is Chriſt in the Fleſh, and Chriſt in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; both theſe agree to make out the Father; and here is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of that work of God within us, from that work of God in Chriſt. This latter is the Truth of the former; <hi>Sanctifie them through thy Truth,</hi> that is, do thou act thoſe things really in them, which are done in a figure for them upon me: There is the Truth. I deſire to cleer up this to you by ſome fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar experience.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:45786:79"/>
               <p> You know that Jeſus Chriſt is ſaid to dye for our ſins, and riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for our Juſtification. Here is now Chriſt in the Fleſh; here is his Miniſtration. Why now, hereupon ſalvation is preached unto men, and it is told, that God is reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for he hath ſent his Son. There is nothing to be done; Juſtice is fulfilled; God is reconciled; he would not elſe have ſlain his Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and made a feaſt for us. Therefore beleeve: Here is the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpenſation; but now a poor ſoul, notwithſtanding all this, lyes under the guilt and weight of ſin; and ſuch a grievious ſin comes to his mind, and not only one, but multitudes of ſins lye upon him; whereby he cannot beleeve or take comfort in theſe glad tydings. Do ye not ſee that there is need of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſtration? Is there not need of the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, as well as a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:45786:79"/> Propoſition of the Goſpel? You come and ſhew a poor ſoul the Propoſition of the Goſpel; <hi>That whoſoever beleeveth in Christ Jeſus ſhal have eternal life &amp;c. And God ſo loveth the World, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves in him ſhould have eternall life.</hi> Yet all this while the poor ſoul lyes dead, til not only the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but the Spirit of the Goſpell comes and appears to him: Till Chriſt appears, not only in the firſt Court, that is his own fleſh, or the Letter of the Goſpell; but in the inmoſt place of all, that is, in this mans conſcience; for we may allude to that place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 24. <hi>For Christ is not entered into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf, now to appear in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray mark it; Jeſus Chriſt did not ſuffer in Heaven, but without
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:45786:80"/> the gate; he ſuffered in the world, but he is entered into Heaven. Theſe words are ſpoken figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; its true, he went up viſibly, to his Diſciples, into Heaven, (that is) a place remote from their ſight, a Cloud received him out of their ſight. The true Heaven (and that Heaven where Chriſt doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the comfort and relief of a poor ſoul) is the conſcience of a poor ſinner, and that is called Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe as Heaven is the place of God, ſo is the heart of man; the heart of man is the place of God. He is ſaid to be the ſearcher of the heart; he ſits there, and wounds, and heals there; there is Gods true place. It is not in the underſtanding of a man, in the notions there, but it is in the heart of a man, thither it is that Jeſus Chriſt is gone. Chriſt in the Spirit is in the hearts of his people, that is Chriſts place, for that is the Fathers place, for he
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:45786:80"/> is in the Father, and he goes to the Father; as it is ſaid, <hi>Touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now you know that the Father, though he be without us, he is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us; he can neither be ſaid to be without us or within us, incluſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor excluſively, for he fills all things, and is comprehended in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. So Jeſus Chriſt is within us; the Father is in the hearts of men, and ſo is Chriſt, and that is the Heaven where he appears now; for do but conſider this, that which follows in the 25. <hi>verſ.</hi> Pray mark it. Now once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſin. That which is rendered, the end of the world, may be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, the end of the age, or the end of that Adminiſtration. That which I note from thence, is this; that Chriſts ſufferings put an end to one world, that world was at an end
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:45786:81"/> when Chriſt had ſuffered, that is, God had diſpatcht the outward diſcoveries of ſalvation, and now he would diſcover it within us; now al that was to be done by him, was within us. He went into the holy place, he went into Heaven, now to appear in the preſence of God for us; and there it is that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſpeaks a word for a poor ſoul: There it is that Jeſus Chriſt ſits, as King, in our conſcience. Chriſt may offer himſelf long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the Letter, in the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Goſpel; but if he appear nor in the Spirit, and ſit in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to quiet them, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have any true underſtanding of the word aright. Chriſt ſets us free by making us Sons, and the Son a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in the houſe for ever. Pray mark it; unleſs we be made Sons, we cannot abide in the houſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; we do not abide in the houſe for ever, by having an eternall title
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:45786:81"/> by Chriſt, but by a real Son-ſhip within us: That ſame which makes Chriſt a Son makes us Sons; and ſo you have it cleared unto you by that inſtance, that this is the truth; and the other, in compariſon of this, is but the form, but the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation or Image, but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of this Truth; and ſo what is it unto us in matter of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſay, Chriſt hath taken hold of our nature, and purified it, and ſeperated it, and ſanctified it: what is this to the ſanctifying of us, if our perſons be not taken into that ſame Union, and be not ſanctified with the ſame Spirit that Chriſt is.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> Now for this Reaſon, I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to look within your ſelves; and I make no queſtion, but if you do wait upon God without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced ſpirits, he wil clear this Truth to you.</p>
               <p>If ſo be it might be no offence, I
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:45786:82"/> ſhould give you my own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the confirmation of this point, (for we can ſpeak nothing, but what we have heard, and what we have ſeen:) Now I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and profeſs unto you, that God hath made real this Truth unto me, not by ſtudy, not by notion, not by outward diſcovery, but by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward experiment: For this I have found, and I truſt more have found it beſides my ſelf, (though it may be they cannot tell what to call thoſe things that work within them, nor how to expreſs it, (it may be) but this I have found, that all outward adminiſtration hath been weak, and unable to produce thoſe fruits and effects which the Scripture makes mention of: it hath been as the Law; <hi>What the Law could not do, in that it was weak</hi> &amp;c. And look into your ſelves, whether you have not found it ſo in your ſelves, that you have had ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:45786:82"/> that hath troubled you: Some maſterful luſt you would be glad to get the victory over, and ye would account him a Meſſenger, one among a thouſand, that could ſhew you how to effect your deſires</p>
               <p>I am ſure, it hath been ſo with me; and when I have ſeen ſuch words as theſe in the Scripture; <hi>Sin ſhall not have Dominion over you, for ye are not under the Law but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have conſidered with my ſelf, and have done as I have been dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to do, and I have told my ſelf thou art under grace, and I have pleaded this to God, Lord I am under grace, I am under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and why ſhould ſin have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over me: and thereupon I have ſtudied the promiſes, becauſe 'tis ſaid; <hi>There are given to us excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great and precious promiſes, that by them, we might be made partakers of the divine nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:45786:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:45786:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:45786:84"/>
               <p> I have looked upon Jeſus Chriſt dying for me, becauſe the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The Love of Chriſt conſtrains us,</hi> &amp;c. When all this while I have been like <hi>Siſeras</hi> Mother, wondering in my ſelf, why do his Chariot Wheels ſtay, &amp;c? Why am I not ſet free from my luſts? Is the Goſpel a broken Reed? Doth it tell us things that we muſt make up by imagination, rather then feel the real operation, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them within us?</p>
               <p>The laſt Scripture I was much exerciſed in, in relation to theſe things, was this, in the Epiſtle of <hi>John; He that abideth in him ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon I enquire what this is, to abide in Chriſt, and ſought to make it out to my ſelf by my own Reaſon, and to find it out by the Letter of the Scripture, and all the account I could give of it, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the creatures action: I
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:45786:84"/> thought we muſt be ſtill comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our ſelves, and putting our ſelves on to abide in Chriſt; and we muſt call upon one another to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in Chriſt. And thus was I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in a continuall toyle and perplexity, and never could ſee my deſires all this while, I could not find my corruptions ſlaine by all theſe means, til God was pleaſed to hold forth this diſcovery to me, which I do now deſire to hold forth to you, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is not the fleſh of theſe things, it is not the hiſtoricall knowledg of theſe things, it is not <hi>the ſaying</hi> you are under grace; it is not being under the <hi>forme</hi> of the Goſpell that can change your hearts, ſet you free from ſin; but it is the <hi>Spirit,</hi> that, when he comes, doth chaſe away all Clouds, as the Sun on the earth. It is Chriſt in the Spirit, who is the truth within you, repreſented by that Hiſtory without you; and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:45786:85"/> yet all theſe things are the making out of God to you; they are not your happineſs, or your life; for our happineſs lies not in any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be it in the greateſt action; not in the <hi>mortification</hi> of ſin, nor in <hi>vivification,</hi> but our life lyes in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that hidden principle within us, that is God. And if ever you would have this Union, and that which is your hope made out to you, and would have the enjoyment of it in this life, you muſt wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Jeſus that came down from the Fathers Boſom, and lived in the fleſh; you muſt wait upon him, to come and live in your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, not only to bring you forth in the participation of his nature, but to fill you with the fulneſs of God, for ſo we have warrant to expect, that you may be filled with all the fulneſs of God. Now this the Lord ſhew you to be a Truth: There is a two-fold Truth; there is a mediate
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:45786:85"/> Truth, and an ultimate Truth; there is a Truth manifeſting, and a Truth manifeſted: Now the Truth manifeſted, is Union; <hi>That they all may be one, as we are one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Truth that God would manifeſt to us by theſe things; by coming to us in the fleſh of Chriſt, and in the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now the Truth manifeſting, is the Appearance of Chriſt in the Spirit, ſutable and conformable to that outward Appearance of Chriſt in the fleſh, without us, for our ſakes: And you wil never have the Love of God, and your Union with God, manifeſted to you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be manifeſted to you by the Spirit, and except God work the ſame works in you, that he wrought in Chriſt. And thus I have diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my ſelf of this ſame Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
               <p>There are but two or three things that I ſhall ſpeak by way of Uſe;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:45786:86"/> and the firſt is this.</p>
               <p>Conſider that which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpeaks, <hi>John</hi> 16. 5. ſaith he there; It is expedient for you that I ſhould go away; and pray mark it here. Theſe times from Chriſts departure, are the times of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>And pray mark that in the firſt place; the Spirit is the power of the fleſhly adminiſtration; he is the power within us, of that fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or adminiſtration without us. The Spirit is often called pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in the Demonſtration of the Spirit and Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Obſerve this, that there is but one Adminiſtration upon the world at a time; there is but one Adminiſtration upon a Perſon at a time: So that, if you be under that Adminiſtration of the Spirit, you are paſt from under the fleſhly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. This is clear from hence, that Chriſt ſaith; <hi>It is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:45786:86"/> 
                  <hi>for you that I go away, for except I go away, the Comforter wil not come.</hi> A ſeed of corn doth not grow up in the eare or the blade, except it dye in its own firſt form; and ſo it is here,</p>
               <p>That which I would infer from hence, is this; That you muſt go quite through the fleſhly Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, before you can come under the ſpirituall Adminiſtration. You muſt ſee the Originall of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and the end of it, that is the Father; the Father ſent the Son, and he ſent the Son to reveal the Father: And it is not in the Death of Chriſt you are to ſee it, it is not in the Reſurrection of Chriſt you are to ſee it. He brings you to the ſight of this, by the power of theſe things working within you.</p>
               <p>And to confirm this to you, I deſire you to conſider; That when as the Scripture ſpeaks of Chriſt,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:45786:87"/> and when Chriſt himſelf ſpeaks to the Father, you ſhall find that the Dialect is exceeding different: When Chriſt ſpeaks to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, look into the 17 of <hi>John,</hi> 11. <hi>And now,</hi> ſaith he; <hi>I am no more in the world, but they are in the world; keep through thine own name, thoſe whom thou hast given me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Scripture ſpeaks of Chriſt to men, it ſaith; <hi>That God hath given him power over all fleſh, that he ſhould give life to whomſoever he will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo the Scripture exalts Chriſt; but when Chriſt ſpeaks to the Father, he doth quite deveſt himſelf, and ſaith, <hi>Father I have kept them through thy name, I have mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted thy name unto them.</hi> verſe 6. Mark ye, Chriſt had made this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery to them, that all the power he had, was of the Father: <hi>And now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Father, I come to thee, keep them through thy name.</hi> It was
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:45786:87" rendition="simple:additions"/> before, by Gods name, that Chriſt kept them, but now it breaks forth more clearly, that it was through the Fathers name; and ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that this is a kind of reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kingdom to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <note place="margin">☞</note> It is true, the Adminiſtration was to go over and over again, that is, Beleevers are firſt trayned up under a legall Adminiſtration, and trayned up under an Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Chriſt in the fleſh, before they come to the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Chriſt in the Spirit; but as Chriſt himſelf, when he is going out of the world, ſaith; I have done all that I came to do: So after a time, Chriſt leads us from a knowing of him after the fleſh, as repreſenting things to us to know him within us, as a quickning Spirit. Conſider how <note place="margin">☞</note> much it concerns you, not to ſhut your eyes againſt this, but exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, and try it, becauſe the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:45786:88"/> truth is, you will make ſlow ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance til you are paſt through the fleſhly Adminiſtration, and are under the Spirit. Look into the 28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. <hi>Whom ſhall he teach knowledg, and whom ſhall he make to understand Doctrine, them that are weaned from the milk, and drawn from the breaſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray mark it, There is a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and there is an anſwer; <hi>Whom ſhall I teach knowledg, and whom ſhall he make to underſtand doctrine,</hi> there's the queſtion; The anſwer is, <hi>them that are weaned from the milk, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſame milk, and theſe ſame breaſts are the fooliſhneſs of God, whereby he had made out himſelf to us according to our infirmity; they are the fleſhly Appearance and Diſcoveries of God; theſe are the breſts, and this is the milk: and till we have proceeded further, we are in the fleſh: And as you will
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:45786:88"/> count it a ſhame for an old man to lie ſucking at the dugg, ſo you are in an uncomely poſture to be always ſucking the breſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways under rudiments, and to know no more of God then he holds forth in an Image without you. This is not your intereſt to reſt here; and therefore I beſeech you to wait upon God, for the humble he will teach in his way. And although I have met with ſome objections againſt this, and more may be raiſed from the Scripture that may ſeem to make againſt this, yet they are made clear to me; therefore wait upon God to clear them up to you. If be this taken from me, I profeſs I know no hope that I have of my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; for what is our hope, but the hope of the high calling? God cals us to fellowſhip with himſelf, and hath manifeſted this by his Son. Weigh theſe things in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:45786:89"/> and conſider that Chriſt comes in Clouds, and not in clear Diſcoveries at the firſt; the Lord give you underſtanding in all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:45786:89"/>
               <head>THE Dying and the living CHRISTIAN.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>ROM. 14. 8.</bibl>
                  <q>For whether we live we live unto the Lord, and whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ERE is the <hi>Unity</hi> of Beleevers in their <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> and the <hi>Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Beleevers in their <hi>Forms.</hi> All Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in what form ſoever, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>bond</hi> or <hi>free,</hi> it is <hi>to the Lord,</hi> there's their <hi>Unity;</hi> but there
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:45786:90"/> are <hi>bond,</hi> and there are <hi>free;</hi> there are <hi>Jews;</hi> thoſe that are <hi>under the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> there are thoſe that are <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law;</hi> there are ſuch as do <hi>live</hi> to the Law, and ſuch as do <hi>dye</hi> to the Law; there is their Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>I have already obſerved this point unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
                  </label> That <hi>God is in all forms,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>distinct</hi> forms, but in <hi>oppoſite</hi> forms: <hi>Whether we live we live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, or whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord. He that regardeth a day, and he that regardeth not a day,</hi> the Lord is in the <hi>light,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the principles of the <hi>one</hi> as well as of the <hi>other.</hi> The Lord is guide and <hi>leader</hi> of him that obſerves a day, and of him that obſerves not a day. This ſeems to be a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, a <hi>Paradox;</hi> God is but one, the Truth is but one; 'tis true, but there are ſeveral <hi>ſteps</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of this Truth: We ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:45786:90"/> come to be all one, and the Name of the Lord will never be one among us, untill God is come forth in his <hi>moſt ſpirituall</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and untill he hath brought us <hi>all to acknowledg that</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but in order to Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out himſelf in his ſpirituall appearance, in his naked diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and with an open face, he doth manifeſt himſelf in <hi>forms,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vails; and he doth put off one form after another; put off a more groſs, and put on a more fine; put off a more thick, and put on a more thin, and ſpirituall, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile vail. God is <hi>in all</hi> forms, but <hi>comprehended of no</hi> form; if he were comprehended in any, then he would not be in a diverſity of forms; There's the great miſtake of Chriſtians; and this ſame dark principle, is that which makes us ſo to claſh one againſt another: We know not the mind nor the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:45786:91"/> manner of the Lord; we think if he be in our form, he can be in no other form: God is in a variety of forms and appearances, that ſo, <hi>no fleſh may glory in his preſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God will not be tyed to one form always, for then that would be lookt upon as <hi>more then a form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have already gone through three things in the handling of this point, which for the help of your memories, I will only name to you; the <hi>expounding</hi> of it, the <hi>bounding</hi> of it, and the <hi>grounding</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>For the bounding of it, tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is the only thing I ſhal now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you of. Is God in all forms? Then every ſuperſtitious wretch will take ſanctuary here. I anſwer thus far; That whatſoever form any man doth <hi>conſcientiouſly</hi> take up, that is a form of <hi>Scripture-cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance,</hi> and doth walk in it <hi>to the Lord,</hi> being perſwaded it is the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:45786:91"/> Lords mind. He hath acceptance with the Lord: For this is the bound the Holy Ghoſt ſets in the Text; He that regards a day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards it to the Lord. Is a man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in what he doth? Doth he it to the Lord? Doth he take it up becauſe he thinks it is the Lords mind? And doth he ſerve the Lord and not any luſt? Not a luſt of honor, and the applauſe of men? Or the profit and commodity of this world? Or the preferment of the time? Why, if he doth it to the Lord, <hi>who art thou that judgest him?</hi> The Scriptures hold forth unto us ſeverall forms (as God hath put on ſeverall forms in his appearance to his people, and the Scriptures are the records of all theſe) and direct us unto them, Now, whoſoever in the ſincerity of his heart, takes up any of theſe, and walks in them as unto the Lord, he is accepted of him.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:45786:92"/>
               <p> Now the Uſe I made of this ſhall not be repeated; but there is one Uſe more behind. I exhorted you the laſt time, that you ſhould hold it forth, that you do obſerve all your forms unto the Lord, and every one bring forth his proper fruit; whether you be in forms, or whether you be above forms: Thus the holy and happy man is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the firſt <hi>Pſalm; He brings forth his</hi> (own) <hi>fruit in his ſeaſon.</hi> Look what <hi>ſeaſon</hi> and <hi>adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> you are under, ſee you bring forth your proper fruit: Thoſe that are in forms, ſee that your forms be <hi>advantage ground</hi> to riſe up to the <hi>Spirit;</hi> Thoſe that be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove forms, let them bring down the glory of God, and the Spirit, upon all forms wherein they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with men; and as God hath brought them forth in the Spirit, ſo let them <hi>bring forth every action</hi> and form wherein they walk in the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:45786:92"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
                  </label> But the main Uſe which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and that for which I did in a main part pitch upon theſe words, is, to reconcile Beleevers in their different walkings and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations: Indeed it is ſad, that there ſhould be any falling out, that there ſhould be any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, as Reconciliation doth import; <hi>Let there be no ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, for you are brethren.</hi> Let us not judg one another, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith here, Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not. If ſo be that Chriſtians do not judg themſelves in their forms, why ſhould we jud<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them? And if ſo be that we do not judg one another, why ſhould we think that we are judged one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for there's the quarrell ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times. Such a man cannot walk in a different form from me, but I think preſently he condemns me, and accounts me fleſhly and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:45786:93"/> carnall: It is a ſign that thou judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy brother in his form, that doſt think that he judgeth thee in thy form; For <hi>ſuch as we are our ſelves, ſuch we judg others to be;</hi> Let us not judg one another, for God hath received him that eateth, and God hath received him that eateth not. Where is the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spirit, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. Is there no u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but where there is uniformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Becauſe we have not ſtill one form, have we not therefore one Father, one Lord, one Baptiſm, or one common condition of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering? Doth not the world hate you, if you be Saints? And doth it not hate them alſo that walk in another form, if they be Saints? Let us not judg one another; the ſtrangeneſs that is among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, becauſe of forms, is ſad to behold; How we are looſened one from another, and how we are loſt
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:45786:93"/> one to another; if we once ſtrike out of that path wherein we have walked one with another; Is not this a denying, a crucifying of the Lord of glory? Is not this a diſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Chriſt in one another? <hi>Is not this a knowing one another after the fleſh?</hi> If you do good to them that do good to you, what reward have you? Do not even the <hi>Publicans</hi> the ſame? So if you love them that are in the ſame form with you, what thank is it? Every man loves him that will ſay as he ſays, and that will build up that which he builds up. The Apoſtle ſaith, That he that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends againſt a weak brother, ſins againſt Chriſt: And is it not ſo; He that judgeth his brother, doth he not judg the Lord in his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? He that judgeth his brother by a form, that overlooks the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Lord in his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſees his deficiency in ſuch
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:45786:94"/> a form; why doth he not now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Spirit (as it were,) and ſubject the divine excellency of Chriſtians and Saints, to fleſhly evidences and tryalls? It muſt make out it ſelf in this fleſhly form and appearance, or elſe there is nothing of God, nothing of the Spirit!</p>
               <p>The Reaſon why we agree not in ſeverall forms, is not becauſe the forms differ, but the fault is in our hearts. God gathers up all forms, and imbraces them in love, and it is becauſe we look not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our brethren in their ſeverall forms, in the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and of Chriſt, that we do not imbrace them too. The Devill carches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>ſpirituall Image and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance</hi> that is under every form, wherein all forms agree, and he fixes our eye upon the very out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form wherein the difference conſiſts; and ſo nouriſhes ſtrife
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:45786:94"/> and diſcord among brethren.</p>
               <p>That which the Apoſtle ſaid of the Law, the <hi>end is glorious;</hi> the end of <hi>Moſes</hi> Adminiſtration was glorious: I may aſſume here, the <hi>true face,</hi> the true Image, and the true and ſpiritual Appearance in and under <hi>every form</hi> is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and it is <hi>God,</hi> and it is <hi>one</hi> and the ſame, but the outward <hi>figure</hi> doth differ. He that hath the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and in that Spirit looks upon all forms, he imbraces them all, he reconciles all, he walks with all, with Jew, with men under the Law, with men without Law; and doth not ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor is an offence.</p>
               <p>All Saints are <hi>one body.</hi> Now as in the body there are ſeveral mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and each member differs as in a figure; ſo in uſefulneſs too, yet are all uſefull in their places: So it is in the ſeveral attainments and adminiſtrations that Saints
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:45786:95"/> are under; each doth differ from other in ſpirituallity, and power, and glory. The Scriptures are a <hi>Record</hi> and Regiſter of all thoſe ſeverall adminiſtrations that God hath brought his people under; of all the ſeverall forms in which God hath appeared to them; and the Scripture bears witneſs to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of theſe, and there is none of theſe but were uſefull in their time, in their order and place, and the one doth <hi>lead</hi> unto the other in a way of <hi>aſcending</hi> ſtill; and as the hand cannot ſay unto the foot, I have no need of thee; ſo neither can the higheſt adminiſtration ſay to the loweſt adminiſtration. I have no need of thee; for there are ſtill thoſe that are benefitted by the loweſt adminiſtration, as well as there are ſome that are raiſed up to the higheſt admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. The <hi>Nurſe</hi> in a family (where there are children) is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:45786:95"/> in her place, as well as the <hi>Steward</hi> of the houſe, that looks to all the eſtate. <hi>Milk</hi> is uſefull to babes, as well as <hi>ſtrong meat</hi> to men: Therefore, as the members of the body do all of them do their office in their ſeveral places, without <hi>diſputing</hi> and murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: (The hand ſaith not, becauſe I am not the head, therefore I am not of the body; nor the foot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am not the eye to ſee the way, therefore I will not carry on the body in the way;) So ſhould it be in the Body of Chriſt. Let us every one in that ſtation and calling wherein we are ſet in the body, miniſter to the Lord; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Nurſes to give to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or whether as Stewards to provide meat for ſtrong men: If we had a right underſtanding of things, there would not be theſe breaches among us, becauſe we walk not all in the ſame way, are
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:45786:96"/> not all in the ſame <hi>form.</hi> It is the <hi>beauty</hi> of the body to have <hi>variety</hi> of parts; The <hi>manifold</hi> wiſdom of God is ſeen in it, his word is <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſeven times,</hi> and he brings forth the ſame truths in more ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and higher appearances, and higher, and higher yet; the ſame Lord is fulfilled <hi>over and over.</hi> They that are yet in the low bough's, may come to the top bough; But here's the Reſolution of all; Thoſe that are yet <hi>below,</hi> being not able to comprehend that which is <hi>above them,</hi> and that which is more capacious then themſelves, they cannot bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to it, nay, they cannot <hi>bear</hi> with it. But ſtill take this for a certain truth, the <hi>higher</hi> you go, and the more God draws you up, the more able you will be to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend</hi> and reconcile all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appearances, and all lower admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, and to diſcern them
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:45786:96"/> all in the <hi>Unity of the Spirit,</hi> and of the appearance and breaking forth of God. But ſo much ſhall ſerve for that Uſe and that Point.</p>
               <p>Now I come to the next Point, and that's the difference between men in their forms, or rather the <hi>amount;</hi> of their difference, what it amounts to. We have it in theſe words, <hi>Whether we live, or whether we dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who is he that <hi>dyes?</hi> It is he that is in <hi>bondage</hi> to outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances, that depends upon <hi>fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> forms.</p>
               <p>Who is he that <hi>lives?</hi> Why, it is he that is <hi>free.</hi> You know, ye often meet with theſe diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Scripture, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>uncircumciſion, Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, bond</hi> and <hi>free, quick</hi> and <hi>dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Liberty is the <hi>next</hi> thing to life, What good doth a mans life do him, if he be not a free man? (I mean ſpirituall Liberty or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:45786:97"/> in the Spirit;) and Bondage it is <hi>next</hi> to death. But upon other Conſiderations, is it here called living and dying.</p>
               <p>But it may be ſaid, is not the Text abuſed to interpret it thus <hi>allegorically,</hi> or to make a <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor</hi> of it, ſhould it not be taken literally?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether we live,</hi> (that is in the body) <hi>we live to the Lord, or whether we dye</hi> (that is, go out of this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) <hi>we dye to the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, beſides, that ſuch an interpretation is to make the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here ſpeak <hi>impertinently,</hi> as being quite from the buſineſs he hath in hand. You ſhall find al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is <hi>croſs</hi> to the Letter of the Scripture; for that is not death that men call death, and that is not life that men call life; For <hi>God is the God of the living and not of the dead;</hi> in that ſenſe, <hi>Abraham</hi> is <hi>alive,</hi> though dead. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:45786:97"/> calls not them dead, nor God the God of the dead, in that ſenſe, but the living, and <hi>all things live to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, he ſaith not, they <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> though that be to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſpiritually, but they dye to the Lord. And if you ask, why ſhould they be called dying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, dying Saints? The Apoſtle will tell you, when he ſaith, <hi>To be carnally minded is death,.</hi> Rom. 8. 6. That which is tranſlated car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally minded, ſignifies to <hi>ſavour carnally;</hi> to ſavour <hi>God</hi> and our <hi>life</hi> carnally, this is death; but he that is in bondage to forms, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours God and life carnally, <hi>ergo</hi> it is death, and he is a dying man. That he ſavours carnally, appears from hence; That he doth reliſh better, and ſavour more the <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of God in an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> then the <hi>strength,</hi> and excellency, and glory of God in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:45786:98"/> in his own <hi>proper</hi> appearance. He is more taken; his heart goes out more after a ſight of God in <hi>fleſh,</hi> then to ſee him in <hi>Spirit;</hi> is not this to ſavour life carnally? For to think that a mans life is bound up in any form, or in fleſh, is it not a carnall ſavour? And yet do not many Chriſtians do ſo? Do not they think that <hi>God and an Ordinance</hi> do nouriſh and feed, and adminiſter ſtrength to you, but not God without an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We have this treaſure in earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi> Now if a man counts not this to be treaſure except it be in an earthen veſſell, is not this carnall? It is true, while we do receive God in any form it is mercy, but to ſay, God <hi>cannot</hi> be meat or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment without a form, this is to ſavour our life carnally. How many Chriſtians are troubled and aſſaulted with doubts, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:45786:98"/> their good eſtate, that have a load lying upon them, and Clouds of darkneſs before them; that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker after an Ordinance to come &amp; diſpell theſe Clouds! O if I could receive ſuch an Ordinance, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in ſuch a manner; This would ſolve all objections, and give them full aſſurance: when as they have God, they have his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; <hi>The word is nigh thee,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>even in thy heart.</hi> But behold, except this God will come to them in fleſh, they can make no uſe of him; they cannot ſee how God ſhould do it in Spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a form; this is to ſavour life carnally, therefore they <hi>linger</hi> in their deſertions and temptations, and are not help't out of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſtay for God to come to them in ſuch a way, and ſee no ſalvation for them in <hi>himſelf,</hi> for then they would depend upon
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:45786:99"/> him. Agreeable to this Scripture is another, <hi>viz. Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>If we live after the fleſh we ſhall dye.</hi> Now there are many ſorts of fleſh, ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>There is one kind of fleſh of men, another of beaſts, another of birds, another of fiſhes.</hi> There is fleſh of fiſhes, that will carry a man <hi>ſwimmingly</hi> like the Spirit; and there is fleſh of birds, that wil <hi>ſoar aloft</hi> like the Spirit; there is <hi>high-raiſed</hi> fleſh, but if we live <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the motion</hi> or principle of any thing <hi>below God,</hi> we live after the fleſh. Even if we live after the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Graces</hi> themſelves, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving our graces into God. If the <hi>ſparkling and turning</hi> of our graces themſelves be the wine, that doth chear and refreſh us; yea, the fleſh of Chriſt, if we ſtick in that vail, (and ſtand not in the naked Spirit of Chriſt, before God, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through Chriſts fleſh, both in him, and in our ſelves, as he hath
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:45786:99"/> paſt through it,) we are not yet paſt out of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>I ſay not, that they <hi>that have the uſe</hi> of forms are dying Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but they <hi>that depend</hi> upon them, they that cannot have life from God, unleſs he preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Reaſon; <hi>They that fall ſhort of God are in a dying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> but thoſe whoſe life is bound up in any form, they fall ſhort of God. He that attains not God, loſes the Race, He that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains not <hi>the prize of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of God in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> loſes the Race, and he dyes. He that is in bondage to outward obſervan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and depends upon them, fals ſhort of God, that is, of the <hi>glory</hi> of God; He hath God under a <hi>vail</hi> in his form, but not God in his glory; He ſees God vailed, not his <hi>open face,</hi> not <hi>as he is,</hi> He hears of God in a <hi>Parable,</hi> he ſees him not <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:45786:100"/> even the fleſh of Chriſt is a vail, and till we are paſt through that (through the Mediatorſhip, and through the fleſhly ſtate in our ſelves,) we appear not in the <hi>open preſence of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>The end of forms is death.</hi> The end of Chriſts <hi>fleſhly</hi> ſtate and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance was death; either we muſt lye and dye <hi>in form</hi> (I mean not eternally,) or we muſt dye <hi>to form.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There's no coming to a higher ſtate but by dying to the former ſtate, Chriſt was <hi>Crucified in fleſh,</hi> before <hi>Juſtified in Spirit; He that endures to the end ſhall be ſaved:</hi> He that paſſes through all things, forgets, and dyes to <hi>imperfect</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, to fleſhly appearances, (let them be never ſuch ſpirituall fleſh,) he only is in the way of this ſalvation here meant.</p>
               <p>The fleſhly form (as it is in Saints) hath in it the <hi>ſeed</hi> and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:45786:100"/> of the <hi>ſpirituall appearance,</hi> and <hi>genders</hi> it by <hi>dying; God that commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs.</hi> God brings forth glory to his people by <hi>affliction, tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and dying. Their comforts go away in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> ere they come in the <hi>Spirit.</hi> While the fleſh <hi>laſts</hi> upon them, the Spirit is not <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken forth.</hi> While the form or fleſhly appearance is any thing to us, and we promiſe our ſelves any thing from it, God is not <hi>all in all;</hi> while God is not all in all, our comforts are not brought forth in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and ſo are not made <hi>perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all fleſhly appearances there is <hi>Enmity</hi> to God, therefore God is Enmity to them, and is the death of them. This Enmity is diſcovered in the diſputes that we have about faith; <hi>Whether it juſtify as a Condition, or as an Inſtrument</hi> only; and about the Spirit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:45786:101"/> the Spirit be in us by <hi>preſence</hi> or by <hi>influence</hi> only, which are miſts that ariſe out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs pit, and argue, God is not all in all there, and ſo that ſoul is not perfected.</p>
               <p>The Scripture in 1 <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> paralels the diſpenſation Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are under, <hi>I wil utterly conſume all things from off the Land, ſaith the Lord. I will conſume man and beast; I will conſume the fowls of the Heaven, and the fiſhes of the Sea, and the stumbling blocks with the wicked, and I will cut off man &amp;c.</hi> and v. 4. <hi>I will ſtretch my hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> (upon Profeſſors;) <hi>And I will cut off</hi> (ver. 5.) <hi>them that worſhip, and ſwear by the Lord and Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham.</hi> This is the condition of our times, light is broken in upon us, and we ſee that Ordinances are nothing <hi>without</hi> the Lord; every one will confeſs that; that the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:45786:101"/> is a dead Letter without the Spirit, and the Ordinances are meer forms <hi>without</hi> Gods Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in them; and therefore our deſign is to <hi>couple</hi> the Lord and Ordinances together, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to hear of the parting of them: Swear by the <hi>Lord</hi> and by <hi>Malcham;</hi> even as you ſee men now adays do, ſo we may have but Ordinances, we are well: This is that which I was ſpeaking of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that we do promiſe our ſelves ſomething from the <hi>fleſhly</hi> form and appearance, and ſo like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> we are hankering after the <hi>fleſh-pots</hi> of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> though they had as good meat in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, yet the fleſh-pots ran in their minds. So, though God offer himſelf, and though Chriſtians tell you (for what they tell you, God tells you,) they tell you they cannot <hi>find</hi> God in ſuch and ſuch forms, but find him <hi>abundantly</hi>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:45786:102"/> good in the Spirit, and they find that he <hi>recompences</hi> the want of all forms in the <hi>Spirit;</hi> though he be gone out of the <hi>Temple,</hi> yet they find him in their <hi>hearts;</hi> they preſs you to wait till God appear to you in the Spirit: Oh (ſay you) I can never beleeve it, that God ſhould do it <hi>without</hi> an Ordinance, or that God ſhould ſtrengthen you without an Ordinance. <hi>God</hi> (think you) <hi>with</hi> an Ordinance can ſtrengthen me, and deliver me, and ſave me out of a tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not otherwiſe: this is to ſay, that the Ordinance or fleſhly form, doth <hi>add</hi> ſomething to God. If you will confeſs God to be all <hi>in</hi> an Ordinance, you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs him to be all <hi>without</hi> an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, to be ſufficient of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>I deſire not to be miſtaken; I do not judg thoſe that <hi>find</hi> God in Ordinances and outward
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:45786:102"/> forms, Let them wait upon God, and let them receive and partake of the benefit of the Ordinance, and let them bleſs God for it, and be faithfull to their own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and let them be ſweet to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but when we do find God in a form, and in an Ordinance, to ſay, he is not to be found and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed any other way, this is not a right Spirit. Nay, when we find not God in an Ordinance, yet we will keep to it, as if God were not to be enjoyed any other way. This is the greateſt <hi>unreaſonableneſs</hi> that can be, to put no worſe a name up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
               <p>Now I have done with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the point.</p>
               <p>I ſhould ſhew now who are the <hi>living</hi> Chriſtians, and how they are in a more living condition that are free from the bondage of outward obſervances, that do not depend upon any fleſhly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:45786:103"/> or adminiſtration, but ſee a <hi>fulneſs</hi> and ſufficiency of God in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and enjoy the ſame; for elſe, for men to have a notion and principle of it, and not to enjoy God in the Spirit; they may come from a ſad outward Religion and forms, to no Religion, nay, to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm; and God will <hi>judg</hi> the <hi>free</hi> as well as the <hi>bond.</hi> They may be free from Ordinances, and yet may be as fleſhly to God, as if they were under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances.</p>
               <p>But the Uſe that I would make of what hath bin delivered, is firſt a Uſe of Admonition unto thoſe that are ſtill in forms; and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a word of Inſtruction to us all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is for <hi>Admonition</hi> to thoſe that are in forms; We ſay not, that the Lord is not within you, nor that which you do, you do not to the Lord; but the holy Ghoſt ſaith of you, you are <hi>dying</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:45786:103"/> While thou canſt only ſee God in a fleſhy Image and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, thou art in a dying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: For it is a ſign, thou ſeeſt not God in his glorious and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Appearance; for if thou didſt, thou wouldſt ſay as they in the Mount at Chriſts transfi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Oh it is good for us to be here: Let us look no more for God in forms, and fleſhly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations; at leaſt, you would deſire to have <hi>your portion</hi> in fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repreſentations; (not but that, that man, who hath God broken forth in him, in ſpirit and power; may ſuffer others in thoſe forms, and not loſe his own enjoyments;) You are Chriſts, and you are Chriſtians, but you are in a fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and dying eſtate, and you may be put ſhrewdly to it, that do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon a form and fleſhly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration: When it cannot be had, what wilt thou do? Thy caſe
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:45786:104"/> is much as a mans that is kept up by <hi>Cordials,</hi> and by means that the Phyſitian uſes to him, and not to be compared with him that is in a way of recovery, that is paſt the danger of his diſeaſe in whom nature is growing ſtrong, and is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercoming the malignity of the diſeaſe by little and little. When the other wants the Phyſitian, it is as much as his life is worth; and the Cordiall, if it be long a fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the man begins to faint; he hath not his ſtrength within him, but without in Cordials; So is the caſes between him that lives upon Ordinances, and him that lives up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt in the Spirit. Chriſt is never <hi>in a journey,</hi> or to fetch a great way off, therefore I ſay, you are in a dying condition that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon forms.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Uſe is of <hi>Instruction,</hi> to give us light in what the Lord is now doing, and in the conſequence thereof.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:45786:104"/>
               <p> You have heard that forms can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpenſe to us the ſpirituall Diſcoveries of God, but by their <hi>going away in themſelves;</hi> then God hath ſent out the Spirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> among us, and God is <hi>contending with fleſh;</hi> and God is come into his <hi>Temple,</hi> to ſit there as a <hi>Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners fire;</hi> and he is bringing down all our forms; But how? He is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying them in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> that he may give us them again in the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that account upon which we may converſe together, and ſpeak together informs; as yet, not in the <hi>oldneſs of the Letter,</hi> but in the <hi>newneſs of the Spirit;</hi> not accounting the form any thing, Miniſters not reckoning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be anointed above their fellows, and ſo making themſelves <hi>Lords</hi> over Gods Heritage. No, it was only Chriſt Jeſus was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed above his fellows, in that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:45786:105"/> Adminiſtration, wherein he was to be of publique uſe to the body, but the <hi>anointing runs down from the head to the skirts of his garment,</hi> &amp;c. The anointing is upon you all Chriſtians; it is the divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance within us anoints us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the world. The Lord hath a quarrell with all fleſh, and we ſhall hear God ſpeaking <hi>in one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> more purely; and he will turn to us a <hi>pure language,</hi> when he hath made us a <hi>poor people.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and Pureneſs ſhall go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And then we will go no more forth to <hi>Malcham;</hi> and when God hath <hi>ſilenced,</hi> and ſtopt the mouth of all <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>he alone is exalted;</hi> then <hi>he will give you Judges, as at the first, and Counſellors, as at the beginning;</hi> and we ſhall all know the Lord, and be able to ſpeak to one another, as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:45786:105"/>
               <p> Think not your Religion will not be, if the <hi>fleſh</hi> of it be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; we ſhall know it more in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and ſee the <hi>anointing</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering it ſelf upon the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:45786:106"/>
               <head>THE Dying and the living CHRISTIAN.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>ROM. 14. 8.</bibl>
                  <q>For whether we live, we live unto the Lord, or whether we dye, we dye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch is the Nature of Man, ſuch our dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and blindneſs, ſuch our unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs with ſpirituall things, that we are even ſhie, and ſtartle at that that is our great intereſt.</p>
               <p>The Diſciples, when Jeſus
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:45786:106"/> Chriſt came walking unto them on the Sea, after he had bin a while abſent from them, took him for a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>cryed out for fear.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord, that Spirit, that quickning Spirit; He hath bin abſent from us a while; namely, during the Apoſtacy, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the raign of Antichriſt, and he is now viſiting us, and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to us in his own appearance: <hi>(When Chriſt who is our life ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,</hi> When he ſhall break forth from under the Vail:) Now we know him not, and are exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afraid; yea, we cry out for fear, we cry out of <hi>deſtroying Religion,</hi> pulling down <hi>Ordinances.</hi> This is the very caſe in the Text here. There were ſome in the Apoſtles days, that were ſtill in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> I mean, that were in that <hi>groſs</hi> fleſh, that were under that ſame <hi>thick</hi> Vail of the <hi>Jewiſh Paedagogy,</hi> and they were offended at others, from
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:45786:107"/> whom God had taken that Vail, and that did not walk in thoſe Obſervances: they did judg them, very like they judged them to be <hi>irreligious</hi> men; What not obſerve a <hi>day,</hi> that God himſelf hath <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted?</hi> Not obſerve diſtinction of meats that God himſelf hath founded? What audaciouſneſs is this to throw down the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, thoſe that did ſee ground perhaps in the <hi>Letter</hi> for what they did, for the caſting off the yoke of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Obſervances, yet not walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpiritually in this liberty, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed</hi> them that were ſtill under theſe. <hi>When any thing of a form is received by our nature, by our fleſh, there is a miſcarriage in it.</hi> If God appear in our forms, we judg thoſe that are above them. If God lead us above them, we are ready to deſpiſe thoſe that are under
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:45786:107"/> them, remaining all this while in deed and in truth, under a form our ſelves, though we appeare in this diſtinction from others, for <hi>uncircumciſion</hi> is a form as well as <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and it ſhews it ſelf ſo to be by this <hi>uncircumciſed</hi> deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of others for forms ſake, in whom there may be as much or more power then in our ſelves.</p>
               <p>In this Chapter the Apoſtle <hi>ſtates</hi> the Controverſie, and gives us a <hi>Rule</hi> to adminiſter towards the one and the other. <hi>Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that eateth not, and let not him that eateth not judg him that eateth, for the Lord hath received him.</hi> Peradventure the one of them is in a better ſtate then the other, yet they are both of them in the Lord, they are the <hi>Lords.</hi> The one is a <hi>Living</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the other a <hi>Dying</hi> Chriſtian, yet they are both the Lords: For ſaith he, <hi>Whether we live, we live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:45786:108"/> 
                  <hi>the Lord, or whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord.</hi> And ſo we come to the words, whence we have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; <hi>That God is not only in different forms but in oppoſite forms,</hi> ſuch as are <hi>regarding</hi> a day, and <hi>not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> it.</p>
               <p>We have obſerved likewiſe what the difference of Chriſtians doth <hi>amount</hi> unto: thoſe that are in bondage to Forms, and thoſe that are ſet free from thoſe forms; the one is a living and the other a dying man. <hi>For whether we live, we live unto the Lord, or whether we dye, we dye unto the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpake of the dying Chriſtian the laſt day, and ſhewed you in what reſpect he is a dying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that is under Ordinances or that depends upon them (for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>converſing</hi> in Ordinances is not a <hi>depending</hi> upon Ordinances:) Firſt, It is a dying condition for <hi>he ſavours life Carnally,</hi> they ſavour
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:45786:108"/> their life according to the <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and not according to the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the carnality of the <hi>forme</hi> and not according to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of <hi>God.</hi> Therefore 'tis that men do put the Ordinances with God, as thoſe that ſwore <hi>by the Lord and Malcham;</hi> they left not out the Lord, but would joyn <hi>Malcham</hi> with him too, they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour life carnally: and ſecondly <hi>they fall ſhort of God,</hi> they fal ſhort of the <hi>glory</hi> of God, <hi>ergo,</hi> they are dying Chriſtians. They ſee God in his <hi>weakneſs,</hi> but they ſee him not in his <hi>strength:</hi> and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>they must paſſe through death,</hi> for every form is raiſed up that it may dye, and not that it ſhould live for ever: it is raiſed up for a <hi>Ministration</hi> to Miniſter to ſome other thing, and therefore muſt have its period. Every form is but <hi>a way,</hi> yea the body of
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:45786:109"/> Chriſt is but a way, <hi>Through the new and living way that is his fleſh:</hi> And I might have added another Reaſon, and that is this, That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>the end of his appearance in the fleſh was death;</hi> He was manifeſted in the fleſh and brought down the love of God and the glory of God in his fleſh: he ſpake the things of God to us in <hi>fleſhly ſigns</hi> and <hi>parables,</hi> and the end of that State was <hi>death,</hi> and ſo likewiſe muſt the end of every State of Chriſtians in the fleſh and in Forms and Ordinances be: The Comforter could not come except Chriſt did go away. An higher appearance of God cannot come but it removes a lower ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God, as a grain of corn doth not riſe up but by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and rorting in its firſt body, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks. But it ſhal ſuffice to have ſpoken thus much concerning the dying Chriſtian.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:45786:109"/>
               <p> But now what is this ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſtian?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether we live we live unto the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who is it that lives? why the Lord lives, and onely the Lord, <hi>they ſhall ſwear, The Lord liveth:</hi> and, <hi>As I live ſaith the Lord:</hi> There is none lives but God, ſo that whoſoever lives, it is by the Lord living in him. The Apoſtle ſaith ſo much, when he ſaith, <hi>not I, but Chriſt liveth in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſame living th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lord in us doth relate unto the dying and buriall of the Lord in us. The Lord he is buried or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured in us, and then he riſeth, as it is ſaid, <hi>I am he that was dead and am alive, and behold I live foreven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> and as it is <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>He that aſcended is the ſame alſo that firſt deſcended into the lower parts of the earth.</hi> And this is the great Myſtery of godlineſſe; <hi>God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest</hi>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:45786:110"/> 
                  <hi>in the fleſh, and juſtified in the Spirit;</hi> firſt manifeſt in the fleſh, <hi>The Word was made Fleſh,</hi> and dwelt among us, &amp;c. And ſo the Word comes, and at length car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries up fleſh with it into ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Indeed we are but the grave, as it were, of the Lord Jeſus. This <hi>whole Creation,</hi> as it is known after the fleſh, and as it is injoyed by us, and as we converſe with it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and as it is carnally received by us, it is but the <hi>Tombe,</hi> as it were, where the Lord is interred; it is but the grave, the ſepulchre wherein the Lord is buried.</p>
               <p>Why then, what is the living of the Lord, the Lords Reſurrection, the Lords ſprouting forth out of this ſame grave, this ſame ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre?</p>
               <p>Anſw. It is this, it is the Lords appearing and the Lords <hi>diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelf,</hi> and the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth and putting off his
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:45786:110"/> Vaile and covering, putting off his grave-cloaths (as I may ſay,) this is the Lords living.</p>
               <p>For the more profitable hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this, take theſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Lords death is the creatures life. The burying or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuring of the Lord Jeſus is the life of man, and the life of formes, and the life of fleſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And in the ſecond place the reſurrection &amp; appearance of the Lord is the death of man, and the death of forms, and the death of fleſh. While the Lord Jeſus hides himſelf, while he breaks not forth in his glory the creature is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and Forms are ſomething, and they grow up and flouriſh as the graſſe doth by the ſhowrs. But when the Lord Jeſus comes forth in his Spirit, and appears, then the graſſe withereth, and the flower fadeth, ſo we finde it in <hi>Eſay</hi> 40. 6, 7. <hi>The voyce ſaid, Cry.</hi>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:45786:111"/> 
                  <hi>And he ſaid, What ſhal I cry? All Fleſh i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> groſſe, and all the goodlineſs thereof is as the flower of the field. The groſſe withereth, the flower fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; becauſe the Spirit of the Lord bloweth upon it: ſurely the people is groſſe.</hi> What is the meaning of <hi>the Spirit of the Lord blowing upon it?</hi> The meaning is this, when the Lord comes forth in his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and reveals himſelf in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then the glory of fleſh paſſeth away, as when the Sun appears in the firmament the ſtars take their leave: we know that as fleſh is enmitie unto ſpirit, ſo ſpirit is enmitie unto fleſh, and therefore it is ſaid, that they luſt the one againſt the other.</p>
               <p>In the third place take this propoſition, That as the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Lord Jeſus is the life of the creature and the life of that fleſh, and the reſurrection of the Lord Jeſus is the extinguiſhing
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:45786:111"/> of the Creatures life. So thirdly, this is, and hath been the deſign of God, and his glory from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; to come forth out of this ſame grave, and from under this ſame Vail (under which he hath lain hid, and been covered) by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſteps; and therefore every ſtep of Chriſts appearance, is, comparatively with the former darkneſs; a ſtate of life, and a <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Chriſt did come forth from under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, when the body was come, then was Chriſt raiſed in ſome ſenſe, and then did Chriſt begin to live and flouriſh; and thoſe that ſaw this, they lived, in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſenſe here, <hi>Whether we live, we live unto the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here was a graduall Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this, though not a compleat Reſurrection. There was a thicker Vail taken off of Chriſt, and a
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:45786:112"/> thinner vail put on: ſo that Chriſt then coming forth under a thinner Vail, is called by the name of the higheſt and laſt appearance of all; It is called a (Living,) not but that Chriſt did ſtill lie under a vail, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Through the vail, that is, his fleſh.</hi> And the New Teſtament Ordinances, though they are finer vails, yet they are vails to the Lord; yea, I may ſay, that the very <hi>graces</hi> of the Saints, as we look upon them in a kind of fleſhly form; as we look upon them in their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar names and circumſtances; ſo they are a <hi>vail</hi> to the Lord Jeſus; yea, Chriſt is ſaid to riſe when he comes into the world; <hi>I am come, that you might have life, and that you might have it more abundantly,</hi> that is, more abundantly then they had under the Jewiſh Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe that was a groſſer vail: In this ſenſe you may underſtand,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:45786:112"/> That <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life, &amp;c.</hi> If you underſtand it in the fleſh, it is in compariſon of the former, a lively appearance of God; Not that this is the higheſt appearance of God, for <hi>to you that look for him, he ſhall appear the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time without ſin unto ſalvation.</hi> So that, I ſay, Chriſt is coming out of the grave, and every ſtep is a ſtep to life, a ſtep of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, a degree of life. Now then from theſe things, if you ask me who is this ſame living Chriſtian, I ſhall anſwer you, firſt, in a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate ſenſe, ſecondly, in an Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate ſenſe.</p>
               <p>In a Subordinate ſenſe, he is a living Chriſtian, in whom the Lord Jeſus hath paſſed through many forms and vails: He that is not in bondage to thoſe ſame groſs, and thick, and dark appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of God.</p>
               <p>But now in the Ultimate ſenſe,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:45786:113"/> the Truth is, that while we are on this ſide, that ſame higheſt and brighteſt appearance of God, till he comes to be all in all in us; we cannot be ſaid to be living Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, though in reſpect of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and darker appearances; the preſent appearance of God to us, may ſet us up in a higher degree of life, yet in compariſon of that which is to come; the very beſt and higheſt of this ſtate is but a death; while God adminiſters to us under any form, under any <hi>vail,</hi> there is ſo much of darkneſs, and there is ſo much of fear and enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt God: and therefore (I pray mark it) thoſe diſputes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us concerning faith; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>the act of faith doth juſtifie us;</hi> or whether it be an act of God that doth juſtifie us; I conceive that herein faith is perverted, and we do make a quite contrary uſe of it then ever God appointed;
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:45786:113"/> he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath ſet up faith, as <hi>a light in a dark place;</hi> and behold we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing that unto faith which is due only unto God. And hence is that other diſpute; <hi>Whether God doth dwell in us only by grace, and be with us only by influences and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations,</hi> as he is in other creatures after their kind: Whence ariſe theſe queſtions, but out of the ſmoke of the bottomleſs pit? and out of enmity againſt God? That grace, and the influences of God will ſtep into the place of God himſelf, they will ſtep into the place of the Bridegroom. Chriſt himſelf in the Spirit, is the grace of the Spirit. So that while God appears unto us under any form, (even grace that is the pureſt vail,) yet God is not all in all: we find faith would be ſomething, and grace would be ſomething, and this is <hi>through the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now there is but one thing more
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:45786:114"/> to do, and that is a little to explain as far as we can, what this ſame reſurrection in a man, what this ſame putting off of the vail is; what the ſtate of a Beleever is in ſuch a condition.</p>
               <p>I ſhall expreſs it to you by theſe two things; By the <hi>purity,</hi> and by the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>The Purity lies herein, that the Lord, he is <hi>all in all:</hi> Here is the Purity of that ſtate; Ordinances they are not, Graces, they are not; the Lord is all in all; the Lord is all in graces, nay, the Lord is all <hi>in himſelf;</hi> he is ſufficient to the ſoul: The Lord is that which Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances were, and that which Graces were, that the Lord is; as you ſhall ſee, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 22. <hi>And I ſaw no Temple there, for the Lord God Almighty, and the Lamb are the Temple of it.</hi> Mark it; what are all Ordinances, but as the Temple was under the Law? The Temple
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:45786:114"/> was that ſame form, wherein God appeared unto his people. It was a figure to them of the body of Chriſt, in which the fulneſs of the God head, was to dwell, and doth dwell: When Jeſus Chriſt came, who was the body, the Temple was no more. So, the ſame compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon we may make between the fleſh of Chriſt, or Chriſt in the fleſh, and Chriſt in the Spirit; What was the fleſh of Chriſt but the true Temple, the body, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that figure and ſhadow that was amongſt the Jews? Thus it was in relation to types that went before; But what was it in reſpect of that which was to come afterwards? <hi>I will ſend you another Comforter, even the Spirit of Truth, &amp;c.</hi> That this Comforter may come, this ſame preſence of Chriſt muſt be removed, <hi>It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for you that I go away,</hi> and <hi>deſtroy this Temple, and I will raiſe</hi>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:45786:115"/> 
                  <hi>it up again</hi> the third day; But when he was raiſed again (I beſeech you do but mark,) did Chriſt let his body be of that uſe to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples after he roſe again? When <hi>Mary</hi> came, and fell at his feet to kiſs them, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Touch me not, for I am not yet aſcended to my Father.</hi> The ſame with that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth know we him ſo no more. Mary</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) my body is no longer a Temple, but your hearts and ſpirits muſt be the Temple; <hi>I am not yet aſcended, &amp;c.</hi> Thou muſt know nothing in me as before; Thou muſt know God in me; I am breaking forth into the <hi>glory of the Father,</hi> and ſhall not appear in the fleſh any more.</p>
               <p>Chriſt in the fleſh met with many an unbelieving ſoul, that went unbelieving away from him; but Chriſt appearing in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:45786:115"/> opens the moſt unbelieving heart. This is the firſt thing in this ſame living Chriſtian; nothing but Purity it ſelf; nothing but God himſelf, is his repaſt, is his delight.</p>
               <p>2. But then ſecondly, This e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate may be deſcribed by its ſtrength and power alſo. It is that which, I confeſs, is a ſtumbling block to the world, (and it may well be ſo) to ſee men boaſt of ſuch attainments above ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and yet to have ſo little ſign of them in their walking and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; to ſee them carnal ſtill, to ſee them dote upon the world ſtill, to ſee them ſtill as proud and paſſionate as ever. My beloved, <hi>you have not ſo learned Chriſt,</hi> if you be living men; if you have the living principle in you, your life is not to diſcourſe in another ſphere and dialect then moſt men do; it is not to be able to contradict, and throw
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:45786:116"/> down the forms of the world. This is not this ſame living man; No, where the Lord Jeſus is broke forth in Spirit, where he is riſen from the dead; <hi>Mighty works will ſhew forth themſelves</hi> in that man; It is a ſtate of power and of glory, and therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>phil.</hi> 3. <hi>That I may know him, and the power of his Reſurrection.</hi> Oh, there is power in Chriſts Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction! All theſe Scriptures belong unto that ſtate, <hi>He that is born of God ſinneth not, for the ſeed of God abideth in him, neither can he ſin, becauſe he is born of God; He that abideth in him ſinneth not.</hi> You have theſe Scriptures in the firſt Epiſtle generall of <hi>John; To them that look for him, the ſecond time ſhall he appear without ſin unto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> Oh, if Jeſus Chriſt doth but put up his head in our Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, he chaſeth away much dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the Sun when it peeps to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:45786:116"/> day, but when Jeſus Chriſt is fully riſen, there ſhall not be the leaſt Cloud, the leaſt corner hid from him; he will detect all corruption there, and divide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the joynts and the marrow. There is no ſuch purifying in the world, as by the preſence and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Lord Jeſus in the Spirit; he purifies, while in him we ſee the Love of God in the fleſh; but when Ieſus Chriſt is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in you, he makes you purifie your ſelves, <hi>as he is pure;</hi> he fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up all from the bottom. This takes you off from I dollizing, not only the forms of your Religion, but the forms of your content in outward things. Let not that man ſay he lives in the Spirit, that is buried in any creature. Let not any man ſay he is above Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that is not above the forms of this world. <hi>If he do not weep, as if he wept not, and rejoyce, as if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced</hi>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:45786:117"/> 
                  <hi>not, and buy, as though he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed not, and uſe this world, as not abuſing it.</hi> Conſidering, <hi>that the faſhion thereof</hi> (theſe forms as well as others) <hi>paſſeth away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a ſtate of power, his prayers are made with ſpirit and life, he enjoys God in every thing that he doth, and is in <hi>Heaven in all he doth;</hi> he wants no command to tell him he muſt do thus and thus; he would naturally do thoſe things, whereby he might ſhew forth the vertues and praiſes of him that hath called him, for he is a living man; who needs ſtir up life, to live, in a living man? Life wil ſhew it ſelf; If you be living Chriſtians, the Spirit of God will work in you, and it will be like <hi>fire</hi> conſuming your <hi>fleſh,</hi> and every day carrying you forth to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and praiſe of God.</p>
               <p>This is a living man, and this is he in whom Chriſt is riſen.</p>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:45786:117"/>
               <p> But one Queſtion more, and that is, of what <hi>part</hi> or <hi>principle</hi> in a man are theſe things ſpoken; Doth this life break forth in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> or is it a life in the <hi>Spirit</hi> only?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that this life is not in any part or principle in a man; It is not in the ſoul, it is not in the body, it is not in the Spirit, but a a man is taken up into this life; It is when we are removed from our ſelves, that we are in the Spirit; <hi>Enoch was not, for God took him.</hi> The Lord takes us into this life; we take not the Lord into our principle; we are not comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this life, but we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended: Here is the miſtake; we ſee men that hold forth ſuch a doctrine and principle as this, and we ſee fleſh, it may be, in them ſtill, and they ſee fleſh in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtill. Do but conſider there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſame place, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:45786:118"/> beginning compared with the 6. <hi>verſe; Now are ye the Sons of God, but it doth not yet appear what ye ſhall be; but when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> Compare but this with the 6. <hi>verſe. Whoſoever abideth in him ſinneth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are the Sons of God, but it doth not yet appear; our fleſh is a <hi>vail,</hi> and while we are in the fleſh, let us act never ſo ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet we fall ſhort of this life; <hi>Fleſh and blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of God:</hi> But if at any time, we are taken up into the communion of this life, it is by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken out of our ſelves; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſaith <hi>Paul, Whether in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or out of the body, I cannot tell.</hi> I conceive, God gave <hi>Paul</hi> an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of that which he will make known to his people in the latter days; and made it known to <hi>Paul</hi> in a viſible and ſenſible rapture:
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:45786:118"/> and whoſoever in the latter days, is taken into the communion of this life, muſt be ſpiritually diſſolved as <hi>Paul</hi> was; for as Chriſt crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fleſh, is but a fleſhly pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of our being crucified in the Spirit. So <hi>Paul</hi> being taken out of the body fleſhly, is but an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Beleevers being taken out of the body into the Spirit; and ſo when we are taken up into him, <hi>He that abides in him ſinneth not.</hi> But when we go to <hi>make out God</hi> in our <hi>fleſh,</hi> behold we cannot make out the glory of this appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in us; when we come to live in a fleſhly principle, I ſay, we find ſhortneſs, and death, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make out the things of God, in viſible and audible ſhapes, as it were; but God makes out himſelf to us, when he takes us out of our ſelves into himſelf without any form; <hi>Did you ſee any ſhape,</hi> ſaith the Lord to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi>
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:45786:119"/> when the Lord talked with you? So when the Lord takes a man into this communion with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he takes him out of the fleſh, off from Ordinances, adminiſters not to him in the fleſh; and thus indeed it is, that only when we are taken out of our ſelves, can we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend or ſpeak of this ſame life in God. A Beleever, when he is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up into God and Chriſt; he ſees that which he cannot make out by all his parts, and all the helps that he hath; he ſees that freedom from ſin; he ſees, as it were, that omnipotency with him; when he is taken up, he ſees him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf perfect, as God ſaid to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, walk before me, and be perfect.</hi> Here is that which he cannot make out to the world. Well may men ſay; Do not we ſee that you are a man; I am ſo, but you cannot ſee what I am, when I am taken up into God. God is the <hi>ſubject</hi>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:45786:119"/> and <hi>recipient</hi> that comprehends us, we cannot comprehend him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>
                  </label> Now all that I would infer from hence, is thus much; I beſeech you that you would <hi>know the things that concern your peace.</hi> O, what a ſad thing is it, that men ſhould run away from life! This is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill heart with a witneſs, <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the living God.</hi> This is darkneſs with a witneſs, when the Creature will comprehend God, and will not be comprehended by God; when we will ſay, <hi>There is no other enjoyment of God, then what we can make out in the fleſh;</hi> No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtate then what may be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to men. Oh, take heed of this, and take heed of deſpiſing thoſe that bring you the glad tydings of peace; <hi>How beautifull</hi> rather ſhould even <hi>the feet of thoſe be,</hi> though <hi>upon the Mountains, that bring</hi> theſe <hi>glad tydings, that ſay</hi>
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:45786:120"/> 
                  <hi>unto Sion, thy God raigneth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt hath been long in a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, he is now riſing, and you have the Teſtimony hereof brought to you by men like your ſelves, and we are not able to make out the glory of it to you: This fleſh is not the ſubject and recipient of this glory; this fleſh is laid by, <hi>But what we have ſeen and heard, we declare unto you;</hi> And therefore, we beſeech you not to depart from the living Lord. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man would be a living man in his health: Every man would be a living man in his trade, would drive a free trade, and will you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be content to be dead creatures in reſpect of communion with God? I beſeech you, <hi>gird up the loyns of your minds, be ſober, and hope to the end, for the grace that is yet to be brought unto you by the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Christ in Spirit,</hi> as
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:45786:120"/> well as beleeve that grace that is already brought by the Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of Jeſus Chriſt in the fleſh. Do but conſider, that God hath always entertained his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with a long expectation of things, ere he hath given them. It was but in the Apoſtles days, that the firſt fruits of the Spirit were given. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> 400 years, before they came to the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> This was but a typicall <hi>Canaan,</hi> and not worth the waiting ſo long for as the ſpirituall <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then again conſider, Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes have been firſt ſown, and dead in the earth of mans unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, before they have been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; witneſs, <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb barren; witneſs, the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> made ſlaves and bondmen; what likelyhood was thereof their being a Kingdom of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:45786:121"/> Prieſts unto God? Nay, from the beginning of the performance, there is uſually an Apoſtacy that comes before the ful accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; was it not ſo when God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to perform his promiſe to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> of leading them into <hi>Canaan?</hi> Did not they fall back in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs? Was it not ſo in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> when <hi>Iſaac</hi> was born, and growing up to his Fathers hope? Then <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt be ſacrificed. So, I conceive, it is here; the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit began to be ſprinkled in the primitive times in gifts, and ſince that, what an Apoſtacy hath there bin? So that the Spirit is yet to be poured out; and now after the Apoſtacy is to be the harveſt. And ſo I am perſwaded many Chriſtians enter into Ordinances, in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>fall back</hi> into the <hi>fleſh;</hi> there remains therefore a Reſtitution, a <hi>latter day,</hi> a <hi>latter</hi>
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:45786:121"/> 
                  <hi>rain;</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, at the <hi>latter day I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh;</hi> and is not the Lord putting up his head in our Horizon? Therefore think not the promiſes of life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have <hi>given down</hi> all they have <hi>travailed</hi> with.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:122"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:122"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:123"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:123"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>LEaſt my meaning in any thing be lockt up from the Readers underſtanding, I thought good to add the key of this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="1">1 There is a two-fold Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Kingdom of God, <hi>viz.</hi> outward and inward; the outward in ſigns the inward in truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the outward and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Adminiſtration are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhed the one to the other, ſo they are diſtinguiſhed, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer gradually in themſelves. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> The outward Aminiſtration, or Letter of the Goſpel, excells that of the Law. So likewiſe in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Adminiſtration or Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:45786:124"/> in us. The firſt Appearance of Chriſt in us, is ſwallowed up of his ſecond Appearance in us: The Kingdom of the Father ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels the Kingdom of the Son; and the ſtate of the Reſurrection of Chriſt in us, the ſtate or likeneſs of his death.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when it is ſaid, that Chriſt in Spirit dwelling and working in our hearts, reveals the Father plainly, whom we ſaw but as in a Parable in his fleſh, or without us. I deſire ye ſhould underſtand alſo, that the firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſt within us doth not give a full and perfect teſtimony and witneſs of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for then the Apoſtle would not have ſaid of ſuch that they ſee darkly; and there would be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a ſecond Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and upon this account it is, that in that diſcourſe on <hi>John</hi> 16. 25. I ſpeak of Righteouſneſs, and
<pb facs="tcp:45786:124"/> Sanctification, and Faith, and Love being forms or glaſſes which muſt all be reſolved into God, at length, that he may be all in all.</p>
            <p>And the ſame thing I deſire may be carryed in mind for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of thoſe diſcourſes on <hi>John</hi> 17. 19. That as the inward Appearance and Working of Chriſt is the truth of the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the outward is but a Form ſerving thereto; ſo the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond appearance of Chriſt in us is the truth of the firſt appearance, and the firſt appearance is but the way unto the latter.</p>
            <p>And when as in thoſe diſcourſes on <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. they are held forth as dying Chriſtians that ſtick in Forms and things outward in the fleſh of Chriſt, I deſire Saints may be aware that there is the fleſh of Chriſt within them, or a fleſhly manifeſtation or appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:45786:125"/> of Chriſt in fleſh in them, which is that that they are not to ſatisfie themſelves withall, but are to waite till they be brought forth with Chriſt in the glory of the Father, till faith and Righteouſneſs and al thoſe Forms &amp; Vails be broken up into one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle view of the Father or God al in all, till childiſh things, thoughts and language be put away, and we ſee God face to face as he is; till God himſelf be a place of broad Rivers and Streams in his own Name, and not under another name; till he make all things new, and bring forth all our injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of him in a new light and a new glory. So much as we are ſhort of this, ſo much are we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der death, though we may be paſt from outward forms, and have the life dwelling in us. And they that ſhall deny this to be poſſible in this life, muſt deny the new <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45786:125"/> to come down from God out of heaven and the expreſſe let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Revelations</hi> Chapter 22, verſes 3, 4, 5. where it is written, <hi>And there ſhall be no more curſe, but the Throne of God, and of the Lamb ſhal be in it, and his ſervants ſhall ſerve him; And they ſhall ſee his face, and his name ſhall be in their foreheads; And there ſhall be no night there, and they need no can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, neither light of the Sun; for the Lord God giveth them light, and they ſhall raign for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they that ſay this body of ours hinders, err, not knowing the power of God, and what that fleſh is that cannot inherit, which is not this body (which is in its ſelf, neither good nor evil) but the ſubject of two Inhabitants, two Men, and ſo is good or evil, as it is ruled by the one or by the other;
<pb facs="tcp:45786:126"/> the old or the new man; Self or Chriſt: the old man may be and is deſtroying in Saints dayly, while the body remains.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are hinted in the precedent diſcourſes more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and obſcurely; I add this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for explanation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45786:126"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
